<prof_activity><title>Improving Outcomes in Patients with SSc-ILD</title><objectives><p>Upon completion of this activity, participants will:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Have increased knowledge regarding the
    <ul>
        <li>Assessment of disease severity and risk of progression</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Have greater competence related to
    <ul>
        <li>The management of SSc-ILD through early diagnosis and screening, appropriate follow up, and timely initiation of effective therapy</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Demonstrate greater confidence in their ability to
    <ul>
        <li>Assess risk progression and select patients for treatment</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
</ul></objectives><goal><p>The goal of this activity is to improve physician education regarding the importance of recognizing disease progression and initiating appropriate and effective treatment in patients with SSc-ILD.</p></goal><tgt_aud><p>This educational activity is intended for an international audience of non-US rheumatologists, pulmonologists, allergists, and clinical immunologists involved in the treatment and management of patients with systemic sclerosis-interstitial lung disease (SSc-ILD).</p></tgt_aud><credit_instr><p>There are no fees for participating in or receiving credit for this online educational activity. For information about your eligibility to claim credit, please consult your professional licensing board.<br/><br/>This activity is designed to be completed within the time designated on the title page; physicians should claim only those credits that reflect the time actually spent participating in the activity. To successfully earn credit, participants must complete the activity online during the credit eligibility period that is noted on the title page.<br/><br/>Follow these steps to claim a credit certificate for completing this activity:</p>

<ol>
    <li>Read the information provided on the title page regarding the target audience, learning objectives, and author disclosures, read and study the activity content and then complete the post-test questions. If you earn a passing score on the post-test and we have determined based on your registration profile that you may be eligible to claim CPD credit for completing this activity, we will issue you a CPD credit certificate.</li>
    <li>Once your CPD credit certificate has been issued, you may view and print the certificate from your CME/CE Tracker. CPD credits will be tallied in your CME/CE Tracker and archived for 6 years; at any point within this time period you can print out the tally as well as the certificates by accessing "Edit Your Profile" at the top of the Medscape Education homepage.</li>
</ol>

<p>We encourage you to complete an Activity Evaluation to provide feedback for future programming.<br/><br/>You may now view or print the certificate from your CME/CE Tracker. You may print the certificate but you cannot alter it. Credits will be tallied in your CME/CE Tracker and archived for 6 years; at any point within this time period you can print out the tally as well as the certificates by accessing "Edit Your Profile" at the top of your Medscape homepage.<br/><br/>*The credit that you receive is based on your user profile.</p></credit_instr><hardware_reqs><p>To access activities, users will need:</p>
<ul>
<li>A computer with an Internet connection.</li>
<li>Internet Explorer 8.x or higher, the latest versions of Firefox or Safari, or any other W3C standards compliant browser.</li>
<li><a href="http://get.adobe.com/flashplayer/">Adobe Flash Player</a> and/or an HTML5 capable browser may be required for video or audio playback.</li>
<li>Occasionally other additional software may be required such as <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/powerpoint/">PowerPoint</a> or <a href="http://get.adobe.com/reader/">Adobe Acrobat Reader</a>.</li>
</ul></hardware_reqs><clinical_context/><highlights/><pearls_practice/><addl_credit_amt/><misc_prov_stmt/><addl_credit_avail><p>All other healthcare professionals completing continuing education credit for this activity will be issued a certificate of participation.<br/><br/>
Physicians should claim only the credit commensurate with the extent of their participation in the activity.</p></addl_credit_avail><sec_element><sec_header/><subsec_element><subsec_header/><subsec_content/></subsec_element></sec_element><contrbtr_group><contrbtr_type_lbl>Content Reviewer</contrbtr_type_lbl><contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c79180d496f2"><contrbtr_nm>Esther Nyarko, PharmD</contrbtr_nm><contrbtr_title><p>Associate CME Clinical Director</p></contrbtr_title><contrbtr_bio/><contrbtr_disclsr><p>Disclosure: Esther Nyarko, PharmD, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p></contrbtr_disclsr></contrbtr_element></contrbtr_group></prof_activity>