<prof_activity><title>Impact of Spliceosome Mutations on RNA Splicing in Myelodysplasia: Dysregulated Genes/Pathways and Clinical Associations</title><objectives><p>Upon completion of this activity, participants will be able to:</p>

<ol>
    <li>Describe the impact in splicing factor–mutant myelodysplastic syndromes of splicing factor 3B subunit 1 (SF3B1), serine/arginine-rich splicing factor 2 (SRSF2), and U2 small nuclear RNA auxiliary factor 1 (U2AF1) mutations on pre-mRNA splicing in purified bone marrow stem and progenitor cells, according to a comprehensive systematic analysis</li>
    <li>Determine the associations between aberrantly spliced isoforms and clinical variables and patient survival, according to a comprehensive systematic analysis</li>
    <li>Explain the functional impact of aberrant splicing of key target genes on erythroid cell growth and differentiation, according to a comprehensive systematic analysis</li>
</ol></objectives><goal><p>The goal of this activity is to describe the impact of common spliceosome mutations on the MDS phenotype, according to a comprehensive, systematic analysis.</p></goal><tgt_aud><p>This activity is intended for hematologists, oncologists, internists, and other clinicians caring for patients with myelodysplasia (MDS).</p></tgt_aud><credit_instr><p>There are no fees for participating in or receiving credit for this online educational activity. For information on applicability and acceptance of continuing education credit for this activity, please consult your professional licensing board.<br/><br/>
This activity is designed to be completed within the time designated on the title page; physicians should claim only those credits that reflect the time actually spent in the activity. To successfully earn credit, participants must complete the activity online during the valid credit period that is noted on the title page. To receive <em>AMA PRA Category 1 Credit&amp;trade;</em>, you must receive a minimum score of 70% on the post-test.<br/><br/>
Follow these steps to earn CME/CE credit*: </p>
<ol>
<li>Read the target audience, learning objectives, and author disclosures.</li>
<li>Study the educational content online or printed out.</li>
<li>Online, choose the best answer to each test question. To receive a certificate, you must receive a passing score as designated at the top of the test. We encourage you to complete the Activity Evaluation to provide feedback for future programming.</li>
</ol>
<p>You may now view or print the certificate from your CME/CE Tracker. You may print the certificate but you cannot alter it. Credits will be tallied in your CME/CE Tracker and archived for 6 years; at any point within this time period you can print out the tally as well as the certificates from the CME/CE Tracker.<br/><br/>
*The credit that you receive is based on your user profile.</p></credit_instr><hardware_reqs><p>To access activities, users will need:</p>
<ul>
<li>A computer with an Internet connection.</li>
<li>Internet Explorer 8.x or higher, the latest versions of Firefox or Safari, or any other W3C standards compliant browser.</li>
<li><a href="http://get.adobe.com/flashplayer/">Adobe Flash Player</a> and/or an HTML5 capable browser may be required for video or audio playback.</li>
<li>Occasionally other additional software may be required such as <a href="http://office.microsoft.com/en-us/powerpoint/">PowerPoint</a> or <a href="http://get.adobe.com/reader/">Adobe Acrobat Reader</a>.</li>
</ul></hardware_reqs><clinical_context/><highlights/><pearls_practice/><addl_credit_amt/><misc_prov_stmt><p><img alt="Interprofessional Continuing Education" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/provider/interprofessional-continuing-education.jpg?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=150:96"/><br/>In support of improving patient care, this activity has been planned and implemented by Medscape, LLC and the American Society of Hematology. Medscape, LLC is jointly accredited by the Accreditation Council for Continuing Medical Education (ACCME), the Accreditation Council for Pharmacy Education (ACPE), and the American Nurses Credentialing Center (ANCC), to provide continuing education for the healthcare team.</p></misc_prov_stmt><addl_credit_avail><p>All other healthcare professionals completing continuing education credit for this activity will be issued a certificate of participation.<br/><br/>
Physicians should claim only the credit commensurate with the extent of their participation in the activity.</p></addl_credit_avail><sec_element><sec_header/><subsec_element><subsec_header/><subsec_content/></subsec_element></sec_element><contrbtr_group><contrbtr_type_lbl>CME Author(s)</contrbtr_type_lbl><contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c791800019c8"><contrbtr_nm>Laurie Barclay, MD</contrbtr_nm><contrbtr_title><p>Freelance writer and reviewer, Medscape, LLC</p></contrbtr_title><contrbtr_bio/><contrbtr_disclsr><p>Disclosure: Laurie Barclay, MD, has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:<br/>
Owns stock, stock options, or bonds from: Pfizer</p></contrbtr_disclsr></contrbtr_element></contrbtr_group><contrbtr_group><contrbtr_type_lbl>CME Reviewer(s)</contrbtr_type_lbl><contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c791806f176d"><contrbtr_nm>Amy Bernard, MS, BSN, RN-BC, CHCP</contrbtr_nm><contrbtr_title><p>Lead Nurse Planner, Medscape, LLC</p></contrbtr_title><contrbtr_bio/><contrbtr_disclsr><p>Disclosure: Amy Bernard, MS, BSN, RN-BC, CHCP, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p></contrbtr_disclsr></contrbtr_element></contrbtr_group><contrbtr_group><contrbtr_type_lbl>Editor</contrbtr_type_lbl><contrbtr_element><contrbtr_nm>Nancy Berliner, MD</contrbtr_nm><contrbtr_title><p>Deputy Editor, <em>Blood</em></p></contrbtr_title><contrbtr_bio/><contrbtr_disclsr><p>Disclosure: Nancy Berliner, MD, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p></contrbtr_disclsr></contrbtr_element></contrbtr_group></prof_activity>