<prof_article_slide_presentation>
    <front_label>Front Matter</front_label>
    <above_title/>
    <title>
        <p>Optimizing Statin Therapy: Role of Patient-Centered Care</p>
    </title>
    <contrbtr_pre_content>
        <p>As an organization accredited by the ACCME, Medscape, LLC, requires everyone who is in a position to control the content of an education activity to disclose all relevant financial relationships with any commercial interest.  The ACCME defines "relevant financial relationships" as financial relationships in any amount, occurring within the past 12 months, including financial relationships of a spouse or life partner, that could create a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Medscape, LLC, encourages Authors to identify investigational products or off-label uses of products regulated by the US Food and Drug Administration, at first mention and where appropriate in the content.</p>
    </contrbtr_pre_content>
    <contrbtr_byline>
        <p>Joyce L. Ross, MSN, CRNP, CLS; Joseph Lillo, DO, CPI; Michael Cobble, MD</p>
    </contrbtr_byline>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Moderators</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c791800b8de9">
            <contrbtr_nm>Joyce L. Ross, MSN, RN-C, CRNP, CS</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Diplomate
                    <br/>Accreditation Council for Clinical Lipidology
                    <br/>Immediate Past President
                    <br/>National Lipid Association
                    <br/>Past President
                    <br/>Preventive Cardiovascular Nurses Association
                    <br/>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
                </p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Joyce L. Ross, MSN, CRNP, CLS, has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:
                    <br/>Served as a speaker or a member of a speakers bureau for: Amarin Corporation plc; Amgen Inc.; Kaneka Americas Holding, Inc.; Kowa Company Ltd.; Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Sanofi
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Ms Ross does not intend to discuss off-label uses of drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Ms Ross does not intend to discuss investigational drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics not approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                </p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Presenters</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c79180b97434">
            <contrbtr_nm>Joseph J. Lillo, DO, CPI</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Assistant Professor
                    <br/>Family Medicine
                    <br/>Midwestern University College of Osteopathic Medicine
                    <br/>Glendale, Arizona
                </p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Joseph Lillo, DO, CPI, has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:
                    <br/>Served as a speaker or a member of a speakers bureau for: Amarin Corporation plc; Amgen Inc.; Kowa Company Ltd.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Lillo does not intend to discuss off-label uses of drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Lillo does not intend to discuss investigational drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics not approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                </p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
        <contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c791800018d7">
            <contrbtr_nm>Michael E. Cobble, MD</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Adjunct Faculty
                    <br/>University of Utah
                    <br/>Director
                    <br/>Canyons Medical
                    <br/>Salt Lake City, Utah
                </p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Michael Cobble, MD, has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:
                    <br/>Served as an advisor or consultant for: Kowa Company Ltd.
                    <br/>Served as a speaker or a member of a speakers bureau for: Amarin Corporation plc; Amgen Inc.; AstraZeneca Pharmaceuticals LP; Kowa Company Ltd.; Sanofi
                    <br/>Received grants for clinical research from: Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Cobble does not intend to discuss off-label uses of drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Cobble does not intend to discuss investigational drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics not approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                </p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Editor</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element>
            <contrbtr_nm>Joy P. Marko, MS, APN-C, CCMEP</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Scientific Director, Medscape, LLC</p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Joy P. Marko, MS, APN-C, CCMEP, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_bulk_info/>
    <contrbtr_post_content>
        <h3>Peer Reviewer</h3>
        <p>This activity has been peer reviewed and the reviewer has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:
              <br/>
            Served as a consultant for: Abbot; Heartware ; Medtronic; Thoratec;
          </p>
    </contrbtr_post_content>
    <supprtr_grant_group>
        <supprtr_grant_attr>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/grant_attribution/kowa_pharm_amer-ieg-txt.gif</supprtr_grant_attr>
    </supprtr_grant_group>
    <body_label>Body</body_label>
    <toc_element>
        <TOCLabel/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro>
                    <p>The goal of this activity is to improve clinicians' knowledge and competence in optimizing statin therapy.</p>
                    <p>Before you begin this activity, please assess your clinical knowledge by completing this brief survey. Answering these questions again after the activity will allow you to see what you learned and to compare your answers with those of your peers.</p>
                </slide_intro>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img/>
                    <sec_label/>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt/>
                    <sec_alt_txt/>
                    <qna_form>3</qna_form>
                </slide_grp>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <toc_label/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <toc_label/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro>
                    <div class="app-loading">
                        <div class="webcomp-player" data-config="en/pi/editorial/studio/configs/2018/education/896814/896814.json" data-playertype="edu" id="cme-video-player"></div>
                    </div>
                    <div id="page_nav_top">
                        <div id="prev_page_nav">
                            <a href="896814">« Back </a>
                        </div>
                        <div id="next_page_nav">
                            <a href="896814_3">Next»</a>
                            <a href="javascript:next_toc();" id="next_toc_link" style="height: 17px;">
                                <img alt="" border="0" class="inline_img" src="http://img.medscape.com/pi/cme/ornaments/arrow-next-toc.png"/>
                            </a>
                        </div>
                        <div class="spacer"></div>
                    </div>
                </slide_intro>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide1.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 1.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Optimizing Statin Therapy: Role of Patient-Centered Care</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 1.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide2.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 2.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Panelists</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 2.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide3.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 3.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Multiple Challenges in Statin Selection
                            <sup type="ref">[1-4]</sup>
                        </h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 3.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide4.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 4.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>What Are Your Patients' Needs and Risks? Pick the Right Statin for Your Patient</h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Clinicians must match the right statin to the patient as an individual</li>
                            <li>Different statins have different properties, breakdowns, and intensities</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 4.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide5.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 5.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Key Points to Get Across to Your Patient</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 5.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide6.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 6.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Relationship Between LDL-C Reduction and CHD Relative Risk
                            <sup type="ref">[5]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>The Cholesterol Treatment Trialists' survey analyzed 175,000 patients</li>
                            <li>For every 39 mg/dL lowering of low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, cardiovascular (CV) events are reduced by 22%</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 6.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide7.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 7.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Begin a Dialog</h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>With a dialog at the onset, many adverse events (AEs) can be avoided</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 7.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide8.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 8.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Choose the Right Statin; Not All Statins Are Created Equal</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 8.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide9.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 9.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Statin Pharmacokinetics
                            <sup type="ref">[6]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>The issue of a drug/drug interaction is very real and most patients treated with statins are taking multiple medications</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 9.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide10.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 10.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Statin Safety in HIV on ART
                            <sup type="ref">[7]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Any medication that is lipophilic, that is going through the liver, has more potential for metabolism pathway issues, especially with patients who have a fatty liver</li>
                            <li>Pitavastatin, approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 2009, avoids the cytochrome (CYP) pathway of metabolism and has substantially fewer drug interactions than other statins. It has the potential to be the preferred statin in patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), especially in coinfected patients</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 10.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide11.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 11.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Intensity of Statin Therapy
                            <sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Not everybody needs to have a very high-intensity statin</li>
                            <li>Ms Ross: You really do not need to use a cannon to get a butterfly</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 11.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide12.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 12.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Polypharmacy and Drug-Drug Interactions
                            <sup type="ref">[7]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Certain statins are much safer when patients are on multiple medications or multiple supplements</li>
                            <li>Foods should be discussed for interactions as well</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 12.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide13.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 13.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>CYP450</h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Some statins do not utilize the cytochrome P450 (CP450) pathway
    
                                <ul>
                                    <li>These statins are effective in treating LDL cholesterol to goal</li>
                                </ul>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 13.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide14.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 14.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Pitavastatin and Pravastatin: Minimal CYP Involvement
                            <sup type="ref">[9]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Pitavastatin does not have the drug-drug interactions that you see with the other statins</li>
                            <li>Pravastatin is also as easy to metabolize as is fluvastatin but, depending on the dose, the patient is only going to get a 20%, 30%, or 35% reduction in LDL</li>
                            <li>In most cases, a 40% to 45% reduction in LDL is needed and pitavastatin would be an option to get patient to goal</li>
                            <li>The main 3 culprits for interactions and myopathy are lovastatin, simvastatin, and atorvastatin</li>
                            <li>Beware of interactions with antidepressants, the psychotropic medications, the azole antifungals, and various antibiotics</li>
                            <li>Combining calcium channel blockers and atorvastatin can cause musculoskeletal pain</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 14.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide15.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 15.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Statin-Associated Myopathy Risk Factors
                            <sup type="ref">[10,11]</sup>
                        </h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 15.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide16.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 16.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Statin-Associated Myopathy Risk Factors (cont)
                            <sup type="ref"> [4]</sup>
                        </h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 16.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide17.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 17.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Main Message Regarding AEs and Statins</h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Let patients know that it is possible that they could have a side effect</li>
                            <li>If they do, tell them to come in and have a discussion to find a cholesterol medication with fewer side effects</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 17.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide18.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 18.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Reassurance</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 18.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide19.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 19.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Risk of T2D Lower With Some Statins
                            <sup type="ref">[12,13]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Educate patients on the differences in statins</li>
                            <li>Different patients are candidates for different statins</li>
                            <li>Much of the country has either metabolic syndrome or is diabetic and has issues with glucose metabolism</li>
                            <li>Clinicians need to think about which statins have the best data in glucose intolerance
    
                                <ul>
                                    <li>That would be pitavastatin primarily, followed by pravastatin</li>
                                </ul>
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 19.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide20.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 20.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>The Challenges With Insurance</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 20.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide21.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 21.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Lifestyle Modifications
                            <sup type="ref">[4,7,14]</sup>
                        </h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Involve a team of health care professionals to address lifestyle challenges</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 21.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide22.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 22.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Myth Busters
                            <sup type="ref">[15]</sup>
                        </h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 22.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide23.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 23.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>No Link Between Statins and Dementia: Randomized Clinical Trial Evidence
                            <sup type="ref">[16]</sup>
                        </h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 23.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide24.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 24.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>The Nudge Into T2D
                            <sup type="ref">[13]</sup>
                        </h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 24.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide25.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 25.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Patient Education: Team Approach</h3>
                        <ul>
                            <li>Clinical inertia can be mitigated by a team approach</li>
                            <li>Physicians, nurses, nurse practitioners (NPs), physician assistants (PAs), medical assistants, nutritionists, and pharmacists can help with patient questions, follow-up, and concerns</li>
                            <li>Office staff can also help with insurance issues</li>
                            <li>It takes a village</li>
                        </ul>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 25.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/896/814/Slide26.png</sec_img>
                    <sec_label>Slide 26.</sec_label>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt>
                        <h3>Thank you</h3>
                    </sec_txt>
                    <sec_alt_txt>Slide 26.</sec_alt_txt>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro>
                    <p>
                        <em>This content has been condensed for improved clarity.</em>
                    </p>
                </slide_intro>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <slide_intro>
                    <p>What did you learn from this activity? Please click on the "Next" button to proceed to a brief survey to see how your knowledge improved after the education. You can also see how your answers compare with those of your peers.</p>
                </slide_intro>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro/>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img/>
                    <sec_label/>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt/>
                    <sec_alt_txt/>
                    <qna_form>4</qna_form>
                </slide_grp>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro/>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img/>
                    <sec_label/>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt/>
                    <sec_alt_txt/>
                    <qna_form/>
                </slide_grp>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label>
            <p>Abbreviations</p>
        </toc_label>
        <toc_type>Sidebar</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Abbreviations</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro>
                    <p>ACC = American College of Cardiology 
                        <br/>
AHA = American Heart Association
                        <br/>
ART = antiretroviral therapy 
                        <br/>
AUC = area under the curve
                        <br/>
BMI = body mass index
                        <br/>
CAD = coronary artery disease
                        <br/>
CHD = coronary heart disease
                        <br/>
CI = confidence interval
                        <br/>
CK = creatine kinase
                        <br/>
CKD = chronic kidney disease
                        <br/>
CV = cardiovascular
                        <br/>
CYP = cytochrome
                        <br/>
CYP450 = cytochrome P450
                        <br/>
DM = diabetes mellitus
                        <br/>
FBG = fasting blood glucose
                        <br/>
FDA = US Food and Drug Administration 
                        <br/>
FMO = flavin-containing monooxygenase
                        <br/>
HCP = healthcare provider 
                        <br/>
HIV = human immunodeficiency virus
                        <br/>
HR = hazard ratio
                        <br/>
HTN = hypertension
                        <br/>
LDL = low-density lipoprotein
                        <br/>
LDL-C = low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol
                        <br/>
MAO = monoamine oxidase
                        <br/>
MI = myocardial infarction
                        <br/>
NAT = N-acetyltransferase
                        <br/>
NLA = National Lipid Association 
                        <br/>
NP = nurse practitioner
                        <br/>
OR = odds ratio
                        <br/>
PA = physician assistant
                        <br/>
PI = protease inhibitor
                        <br/>
PUFA = polyunsaturated fatty acid
                        <br/>
RCT = randomized controlled trial
                        <br/>
T2D = type 2 diabetes
                    </p>
                </slide_intro>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>References</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro>
                    <ol>
                        <li>Ansell BJ. Not getting to goal: the clinical costs of noncompliance. 
                            <em>J Manag Care Pharm</em>. 2008;14:9-15.
                        </li>
                        <li>Meade LT. Barriers to achieving LDL cholesterol goals. 
                            <em>US Pharm</em> 2007;32:66-71.
                        </li>
                        <li>Vogeli C, Shields AE, Lee TA, et al. Multiple chronic conditions: prevalence, health consequences, and implications for quality, care management, and costs. 
                            <em>J Gen Intern Med. </em>2007;22(suppl 3):391-395.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ito M, Maki KC, Brinton EA, et al. Muscle symptoms in statin users, associations with cytochrome P450, and membrane transporter inhibitor use: a subanalysis of the USAGE study
                            <em>. J Clin Lipidol</em>. 2014;8:69-76.
                        </li>
                        <li>Robinson JG, Smith B, Maheshwari N, Schrott H. Pleiotropic effects of statins: benefit beyond cholesterol reduction? a meta-regression analysis. 
                            <em>J Am Coll Cardiol</em>. 2005;46:1855-1862.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ross JL. Pharmacology of lipid-lowering medications. In: Wiggins BS,Saseen JJ, Spinler SA, eds. Pharmacist's Guide to Lipid Management. 2nd ed. Lenexa, KS: American College of Clinical Pharmacy; 2014.</li>
                        <li>Jacobson TA, Maki KC, Orringer CE, et al. National Lipid Association recommendations for patient-centered management of dyslipidemia: Part 2. 
                            <em>J Clin Lipidol. </em>2015;9:S1-122 e121.
                        </li>
                        <li>Stone NJ, Robinson JG, Lichtenstein AH, et al. 2013 ACC/AHA guideline on the treatment of blood cholesterol to reduce atherosclerotic cardiovascular risk in adults: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines. 
                            <em>J Am Coll Cardiol. </em>2014;63:2889-2934.
                        </li>
                        <li>Characteristics of the various statins. PL Detail-Document 280502. 
                            <em>Pharmacist's Letter/Prescriber's Letter. </em>2012;6:280606.
                        </li>
                        <li>Stroes ES, Thompson PD, Corsini A, et al. Statin-associated muscle symptoms: impact on statin therapy-European Atherosclerosis Society Consensus Panel Statement on Assessment, Aetiology and Management. 
                            <em>Eur Heart J</em>. 2015;36:1012-1022.
                        </li>
                        <li>Pasternak RC, Smith SC Jr, Bairey-Merz CN, et al. ACC/AHA/NHLBI clinical advisory on the use and safety of statins. 
                            <em>J Am Col Cardiol</em>. 2002;40:567-572.
                        </li>
                        <li>Sattar et al. Statins and risk of incident diabetes: a collaborative meta-analysis of randomized statin trials. 
                            <em>Lancet</em> 2010;375:735-742.
                        </li>
                        <li>Vallejo-Vaz AJ, Kondapally Seshasai SR, Kurogi K, et al. Effect of pitavastatin on glucose, HbA1c and incident diabetes: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled clinical trials in individuals without diabetes. 
                            <em>Atherosclerosis</em>. 2015;241:409-418.
                        </li>
                        <li>Jacobson TA, Maki KC, Orringer CE, et al. National Lipid Association recommendations for patient-centered management of dyslipidemia: part 2. 
                            <em>J Clin Lipidol</em>. 2015;9(6 Suppl):S1-S122.
                        </li>
                        <li>Srinivas NR. Cranberry juice ingestion and clinical drug-drug interaction potentials; review of case studies and perspectives. 
                            <em>J Pharm Pharm Sci. </em>2013;16:289-303.
                        </li>
                        <li>Orringer CE, Jacobson TA, Saseen JJ, et al. Update on the use of PCSK9 inhibitors in adults: recommendations from an Expert Panel of the National Lipid Association. 
                            <em>J Clin Lipidol. </em>2017;11:880-890
                        </li>
                        <li>Ott BR, Daiello LA, Dahabreh IJ, et al. Do statins impair cognition? A systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. 
                            <em>J Gen Intern Med. </em>2015;30:348-358.
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </slide_intro>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <back_label>Back Matter</back_label>
    <ref_grp>
        <ref_item/>
    </ref_grp>
    <cpyrt_holder>
        <p>Medscape, LLC</p>
    </cpyrt_holder>
    <cpyrt_ovrd/>
    <disclmr_ovrd/>
    <bkmtr_front>
        <p>
            <strong>Disclaimer</strong>
        </p>
        <p>The educational activity presented above may involve simulated case-based scenarios. The patients depicted in these scenarios are fictitious and no association with any actual patient is intended or should be inferred.</p>
        <p>The material presented here does not necessarily reflect the views of Medscape, LLC, or companies that support educational programming on medscape.org. These materials may discuss therapeutic products that have not been approved by the US Food and Drug Administration and off-label uses of approved products. A qualified healthcare professional should be consulted before using any therapeutic product discussed. Readers should verify all information and data before treating patients or employing any therapies described in this educational activity.</p>
    </bkmtr_front>
    <bkmtr_glossary/>
    <bkmtr_ack/>
    <bkmtr_discl/>
    <bkmtr_funding/>
    <bkmtr_reprnt_addr/>
    <bkmtr_abbr_notes/>
    <bkmtr_last/>
    <img_ttl_bkgrd/>
    <img_publ_logo/>
</prof_article_slide_presentation>
