<prof_article>
    <front_label>Front Matter</front_label>
    <above_title>
        <p>
            <a href="/sites/advances/hyperhidrosis">Clinical Advances in Hyperhidrosis Management</a>
        </p>
    </above_title>
    <title>
        <p>Sweating the Details! How Would You Manage These Cases?</p>
    </title>
    <contrbtr_pre_content>
        <p>As an organization accredited by the ACCME, Medscape, LLC, requires everyone who is in a position to control the content of an education activity to disclose all relevant financial relationships with any commercial interest.  The ACCME defines "relevant financial relationships" as financial relationships in any amount, occurring within the past 12 months, including financial relationships of a spouse or life partner, that could create a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Medscape, LLC, encourages Authors to identify investigational products or off-label uses of products regulated by the US Food and Drug Administration, at first mention and where appropriate in the content.</p>
    </contrbtr_pre_content>
    <contrbtr_byline>
        <p>Jennifer Cather, MD</p>
    </contrbtr_byline>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Faculty</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c791806a8964">
            <contrbtr_nm>Jennifer Cather, MD</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Medical Director
                    <br/>Modern Research Associates
                    <br/>Dallas, Texas
                </p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Jennifer Cather, MD, has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:
                    <br/>Served as an advisor or consultant for: AbbVie Inc.; Celgene Corporation; Eli Lilly and Company; Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; UCB Pharma, Inc.;
                    <br/>Served as a speaker or a member of a speakers bureau for: AbbVie Inc.; Celgene Corporation; Eli Lilly and Company; Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc.;
                    <br/>Received grants for clinical research from: AbbVie Inc.; Celgene Corporation; Corrona; Eli Lilly and Company; Foamix; Galderma Laboratories, L.P.; Janssen Pharmaceuticals; LEO Pharma; Menlo Therapeutics; Merck &amp; Co., Inc.; Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation; UCB Pharma, Inc.;
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Cather does intend to discuss off-label uses of drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Cather does not intend to discuss investigational drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics not approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                </p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Editors</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element>
            <contrbtr_nm>Shari J. Dermer, PhD</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Scientific Director, Medscape, LLC</p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Shari J. Dermer, PhD has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
        <contrbtr_element>
            <contrbtr_nm>Heather Lewin, MAT</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Associate Scientific Director, Medscape, LLC</p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Heather Lewin, MAT, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
        <contrbtr_element>
            <contrbtr_nm>Eileen A. McCaffrey</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Medical Writer</p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Eileen A. McCaffrey has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_bulk_info/>
    <contrbtr_post_content>
        <p>This activity has been peer reviewed and the reviewer has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
    </contrbtr_post_content>
    <supprtr_grant_group>
        <supprtr_grant_attr>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/grant_attribution/dermira_inc-ieg-txt.gif</supprtr_grant_attr>
    </supprtr_grant_group>
    <body_label>Body</body_label>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The following cases are modeled on the interactive grand rounds approach. The questions within the activity are designed to test your current knowledge. After each question, you will be able to see whether you answered correctly and read evidence-based information that supports the most appropriate answer choice. The questions are designed to challenge you; you will not be penalized for answering the questions incorrectly. At the end of the activity, there will be a short post-test assessment based on the material presented.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1: Maya</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table align="left" border="1" bordercolor="#b3b3b3" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" style="margin-right: 20px;">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="center">
                                    <img alt="" border="0" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/258/902258-patient1.jpg?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=200:150" width="200"/>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p style="min-height: 230px;">Maya, a 33-year-old woman, presents to her primary care clinician with complaints of severe and spontaneous sweating on underarms and hands. Symptoms have persisted since childhood and do not respond to over-the-counter (OTC) antiperspirants. She recently discussed the problem with a pharmacist, who recommended seeing a clinician. She appears nervous, wiping her hand on the examining gown prior to shaking hands with the clinician.</p>
                    <p>Sweating impacts her job as a notary, causing difficulty with holding a pen and shaking hands with clients. She lives and works in a semirural section of the Southeast United States, where humidity is high. Wearing black to hide sweat stains is both unfashionable and uncomfortably warm. Her husband makes what she views as insensitive jokes about her sweating. He suggests that she shower and change clothes more often, or that she lose weight. Losing about 10 lb several years did not reduce her sweating. She has regained the weight.</p>
                    <p>Her medical history is significant for obesity (5'7", 198 lb; body mass index [BMI], 31 kg/m
                        <sup>2</sup>) since adolescence. She has no other medical conditions and takes no medications.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>3</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Burden of HH</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>HH is characterized by sweating in excess of what is required to maintain body temperature.
                        <sup type="ref">[1]</sup> Lifetime prevalence rates of 1.0% to 1.6% have been reported for the United States and United Kingdom, respectively, based on healthcare databases.
                        <sup type="ref">[2]</sup> A US-based online survey yielded a self-reported prevalence rate of 4.8%.
                        <sup type="ref">[3]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>HH can be focal or generalized. Commonly affected focal sites include the palmar and plantar areas, the axillae, and the craniofacial, inguinal, and gluteal areas.
                        <sup type="ref">[4,5]</sup> Nearly two-thirds of patients reported a family history of the condition in 2 series (62% and 65%), suggesting a genetic basis for the disease in at least some cases.
                        <sup type="ref">[6,7]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>The pathophysiology of HH is not well understood but the condition is thought to be caused by sympathetic overstimulation of the eccrine sweat glands.
                        <sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Individuals with HH have higher expression of acetylcholine and α-7 neuronal nicotinic receptor subunits in the sympathetic ganglia, as well as larger-diameter thoracic sympathetic ganglia, compared with non-HH controls.
                        <sup type="ref">[9]</sup> Increased acetylcholine expression in the ganglia may relate to hyperactivity of the central portion of the sympathetic nervous system.
                        <sup type="ref">[9,10]</sup> Sweat glands of patients with primary HH (ie, HH not related to medications or other medical conditions) are normal in size and number.
                        <sup type="ref">[10]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>HH significantly impacts patients' functionality and quality of life. Beyond the substantial embarrassment and anxiety that patients report (85% and 71%, respectively),
                        <sup type="ref">[3]</sup> 63% note occupational impairment and more than 50% describe moderate to severe effect on personal relationships and social situations.
                        <sup type="ref">[11]</sup> The condition also affects choice of exercise and recreational pursuits (eg, playing musical instruments, knitting), and for patients with palmar HH, many manual activities (opening jars, using hand tools, handing things to people).
                        <sup type="ref">[12]</sup> Patients often describe repeated daily showering, changing clothes, and antiperspirant applications in an effort to offset the effects of excessive sweating, which is unrelated to personal hygiene.
                        <sup type="ref">[11,12]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Primary HH presents differently than HH secondary to medical conditions or medications.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>4</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>A retrospective chart review of 415 patients
                        <strong></strong>concluded that meeting the following criteria was associated with a 99% sensitivity and 82% specificity for diagnosing primary HH: focal, visible sweating that is excessive compared with thermoregulatory need, persisting for at least 6 months 
                        <em>and </em>at least
                        <em></em>4 of the following characteristics: symptoms primarily involving the axillae, palms, soles, or craniofacial areas; symptoms that are bilateral and relatively symmetrical; episodes occurring at least weekly; no sweating during sleep; onset younger than age 25; family history of excessive sweating; and impairment of daily activities.
                        <strong></strong>More than 93% of patients in this evaluation (387/415) had primary HH; the rest had secondary HH.
                        <sup type="ref">[5]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1, Continued: History and Physical Examination</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Maya reports experiencing excessive sweating episodes multiple times each week since early childhood. The sweating affects both underarms and both hands equally. Excessive sweating occurs during both calm and stressful situations and at all times of the day, with no identifiable triggers. It does not occur during sleep. Maya reports that excessive sweating and the fear and anxiety around whether she will sweat causes her significant stress. She knows of no family history of the disorder. Physical examination reveals beads of sweat pooling in the palms and wet rings on the exam gown in the axillary area.</p>
                    <p>Maya keeps wipes and towels in her desk at work to clean off her hands prior to scheduled client meetings but walk-ins can catch her unprepared. She stores a towel in her car to help with gripping the steering wheel and uses a paperweight rather than her hand to hold down documents while signing them. She feels disadvantaged at business and social functions, where she is reluctant to shake hands, share meals, or hold a cocktail glass.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>5</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Causes of Secondary HH</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>HH is associated with many common medical conditions (
                        <strong>Table 1</strong>).
                        <sup type="ref">[4]</sup> Medications also can cause HH (
                        <a href="https://www.sweathelp.org/pdf/drugs_2009.pdf">https://www.sweathelp.org/pdf/drugs_2009.pdf</a>
                        <a href="">)</a>. Possible causes of secondary HH should be ruled out prior to starting treatment based on a diagnosis of primary HH.
                        <sup type="ref">[4]</sup> Fever, chills, night sweats, or weight loss over the prior year should trigger an evaluation for an underlying condition other than HH.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>
                        <strong>Table 1. Common Conditions Associated With Secondary HH
                            <sup type="ref">[4]</sup>
                        </strong>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Acute febrile illness (eg, infection)
                                    <br/>Alcoholism
                                    <br/>Diabetes mellitus
                                    <br/>Gout
                                    <br/>Heart failure
                                    <br/>Hyperthyroidism
                                    <br/>Lymphoma
                                    <br/>Menopause
                                    <br/>Obesity
                                    <br/>Parkinson disease
                                    <br/>Pregnancy
                                </td>
                                <td>Rheumatoid arthritis
                                    <br/>Arteriovenous fistula
                                    <br/>Blue rubber bleb nevus syndrome
                                    <br/>Cold erythema
                                    <br/>Drugs
                                    <br/>Glomus tumors
                                    <br/>Klippel-Trenaunay syndrome
                                    <br/>Local heat
                                    <br/>Maffucci syndrome
                                    <br/>Organoid and sudoriparous nevi
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Weight and HH</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The rates of primary HH were similar in leaner (BMI &lt;24.9 kg/m
                        <sup>2</sup>; 12.0%) and overweight/obese patients (BMI &gt;24.9 kg/m
                        <sup>2</sup>; 12.8%) in a survey of individuals attending dermatology outpatient clinics (N=2028). Individuals with late-onset HH (&gt;30 years old) were significantly more likely to be overweight or obese, however (7.7% and 2.7%, higher and lower BMI, respectively; 
                        <em>P </em>=.000).
                        <sup type="ref">[13]</sup> The frequency of HH in children and adolescents ages 5 to 17 years was similar across BMI categories in a retrospective analysis of health system data (N=248,775).
                        <sup type="ref">[14]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1, Continued</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Maya takes no medications and reports no history of fever, chills, night sweats, or weight loss within the last year. Her health maintenance records are up to date and reveal no indication of diabetes, thyroid disease, or other common underlying condition associated with HH. She is diagnosed with primary HH.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Treatment Options</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Therapies for HH include topical antiperspirants, topical and oral anticholinergics, injected botulinum toxin A, device-based therapies, and surgery. 
                        <strong>Table 2</strong> summarizes efficacy data for therapies other than topical antiperspirants and surgery.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>
                        <strong>Table 2. HH Therapies</strong>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>
                                    <strong>Treatment</strong>
                                </th>
                                <th>
                                    <strong>Efficacy</strong>
                                </th>
                                <th>
                                    <strong>FDA Approval Status for HH</strong>
                                </th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th colspan="3">
                                    <strong>Topical</strong>
                                </th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Glycopyrronium cloth 2.5%
                                    <sup type="ref">[15]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>Significantly reduced axillary gravimetric sweat production vs vehicle at 4 weeks</td>
                                <td>Primary axillary HH ≥9 years old; June 2018</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Oxybutynin gel 10%
                                    <sup type="ref">[16]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>Significantly reduced axillary, palmar, and plantar sweating vs control-treated contralateral areas at 4 weeks*</td>
                                <td>Off-label</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th colspan="3">
                                    <strong>Oral</strong>
                                </th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Oxybutynin
                                    <sup type="ref">[17]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>Improved symptoms in average of 76% of patients; 16-study review</td>
                                <td>Off-label</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Glycopyrrolate
                                    <sup type="ref">[18]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>67% response rate; retrospective chart review</td>
                                <td>Off-label</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th colspan="3">
                                    <strong>Injection</strong>
                                </th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Botulinum toxin A (onabotulinumtoxinA)
                                    <sup type="ref">[19]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>94% responders
                                    <sup>†</sup> at 4 weeks; 82% responders at 16 weeks
                                </td>
                                <td>Severe primary axillary HH in adults inadequately managed with topical agents; July 2004</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th colspan="3">
                                    <strong>Devices</strong>
                                </th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Tap water iontophoresis
                                    <sup type="ref">[20]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>92% reduction in mean gravimetric sweat production in palmar HH after 2 weeks (5×/week, 20 minutes each)</td>
                                <td>Approved by the FDA for HH
                                    <sup>‡</sup>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Microwave thermolysis
                                    <sup type="ref">[21]</sup>
                                </td>
                                <td>90% responders
                                    <sup>†</sup> at 6 months post-therapy, axillary HH
                                </td>
                                <td>Primary axillary
                                    <br/>HH; January 2011 (miraDry®)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <blockquote>*Blinded photographic comparisons of the Minor starch-iodine test results.
                        <br/>
                        <sup>†</sup>≥50% reduction vs baseline in axillary gravimetric sweat production after 1 treatment session.
                        <sup type="ref">[19]</sup>
                        <br/>
                        <sup>‡</sup>Drionic, Hidrex USA, and R.A. Fisher, [IHHS, 
                        <a href="https://www.sweathelp.org/hyperhidrosis-treatments/iontophoresis.html">https://www.sweathelp.org/hyperhidrosis-treatments/iontophoresis.html</a>].
                    </blockquote>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <em>Topical antiperspirants</em>. Over-the-counter (OTC) or prescription-strength antiperspirants containing up to 25% aluminum work by blocking the eccrine sweat gland ducts.
                        <sup type="ref">[1]</sup> Efficacy has been documented in patients with axillary (20% aluminum chloride hexahydrate),
                        <sup type="ref">[22]</sup> palmar (aluminum chloride hexahydrate 20%),
                        <sup type="ref">[23]</sup> and plantar (12.5% and 30% aluminum chloride)
                        <sup type="ref">[24]</sup> HH. Side effects include rash, irritation, itching, and stinging.
                        <sup type="ref">[1]</sup> An OTC lotion containing 15% aluminum sesquichlorohydrate and eucalyptus oil for the hands and feet is available (Carpe antiperspirant lotion).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <em>A topical anticholinergic cloth (glycopyrronium </em>2.4%) received FDA approval for use in primary axillary HH based on 2 identical phase 3 trials (N=697). Self-reported sweating severity was measured using the Axillary Sweating Daily Diary (ASDD), a patient-reported outcome (PRO) measure formulated to FDA standards (
                        <strong>Figure 1</strong>).
                        <sup type="ref">[25]</sup> A higher proportion of patients receiving active therapy reported at least a 4-point improvement in axillary sweating severity at 4 weeks, the coprimary endpoint (60% vs 28%; 
                        <em>P </em>&lt;.001).
                        <sup type="ref">[15]</sup> Anticholinergic adverse reactions included dry mouth (24%), mydriasis (7%), blurred vision (4%), and urinary hesitation (4%). Local skin reactions occurred at similar frequency with active therapy and vehicle (31% and 30%, respectively).
                        <sup type="ref">[15]</sup> A 44-week long-term safety trial reported similar findings, with efficacy generally maintained from the pivotal trials.
                        <sup type="ref">[26]</sup> The premoistened cloth is applied once daily to clean, dry skin.
                        <sup type="ref">[27]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>
                        <strong>Figure 1. Axillary Sweating Daily Diary</strong>
                        <sup type="ref">[25]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/258/902258-fig1.jpg"/>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <em>A topical anticholinergic gel</em> (oxybutynin gel 10%) that is FDA-approved for overactive bladder has demonstrated efficacy when used off-label in axillary (n=23), palmar (n=22), and plantar (n=16) HH.
                        <sup type="ref">[16]</sup> Approximately 74% and 62% of patients reported improvement on the HDSS (
                        <strong>Figure 2</strong>) and the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI; moderate or very significant effect), respectively. Patients applied the gel twice daily for 30 days to clean, dry, intact skin.
                        <sup type="ref">[16]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>
                        <strong>Figure 2. HH Disease Severity Scale (HDSS)
                            <sup type="ref">[28]</sup>
                        </strong>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/258/902258-fig2.jpg"/>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <em>Oral anticholinergics</em>. A 16-study systematic review found that oral oxybutynin improved quality of life in approximately three-quarters of patients with HH, though a similar proportion of patients taking oxybutynin 10 mg/day developed dry mouth. Outcome measures with oral glycopyrrolate  therapy in this review were deemed too variable to collate.
                        <sup type="ref">[17]</sup> A retrospective chart review of 45 patients receiving oral glycopyrrolate  (generally 1 to 2 mg/day) showed a 33% failure rate due to intolerance (dry mouth, gastrointestinal effects) or nonresponse.
                        <sup type="ref">[5]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <em>Botulinum toxin</em>
                        <em>A</em> is an acetylcholine release inhibitor for primary axillary HH administered as 50 U total botulinum toxin type A per axilla as multiple intradermal injections per treatment.
                        <sup type="ref">[19]</sup> In addition to reducing axillary sweat production, botulinum toxin A injections were associated with a significantly higher patient satisfaction score at 4 weeks post-treatment (n=242) compared with placebo (n=78) (3.3 vs 0.8 on a scale of 0 to 4, where 4 = complete abolition of signs and symptoms; 
                        <em>P </em>&lt; .001). The safety profile was similar to that of placebo; 5% of subjects receiving active therapy reported an increase in non-axillary sweating.
                        <sup type="ref">[19]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>More than a quarter (28%) of subjects retained efficacy after a single treatment session during a 16-month follow-up period. Among the 72% who required a second treatment to control symptoms, mean duration of efficacy was 30.6 weeks. The most frequent treatment-related side effects were sweating (4%) and injection site pain (2%).
                        <sup type="ref">[29]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <em>Iontophoresis. </em>This therapy involves delivering 15 to 20 milliamps of current through tap water, with patients placing hands or feet in water trays.
                        <sup type="ref">[1]</sup> The reasons for its efficacy in palmar and plantar HH are unclear but iontophoresis has a long history of safety and efficacy. Patients typically use the therapy at home 3 to 4 times weekly, followed by maintenance therapy of once weekly or less.
                        <sup type="ref">[20,30,31]</sup> Covering the skin -- especially nonintact skin -- with petroleum jelly before therapy can prevent erythema or vesiculation. Other side effects include burning sensation or "pins and needles." Crushed anticholinergic tablets (eg, glycopyrrolate) can be added to the water.
                        <sup type="ref">[31]</sup> Nearly 80% of patients reported improvement with iontophoresis after 2 weeks (HDSS).
                        <sup type="ref">[20]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>
                        <strong>Figure 3. Iontophoresis</strong>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/258/902258-fig3.jpg"/>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <em>Microwave thermolysis. </em>This procedure delivers microwave energy to the axillae using a handheld wand, following administration of lidocaine-based anesthesia. Post-treatment side effects including edema and tenderness typically last about 3 days and are managed with ibuprofen. Other reported side effects include redness, bruising, lumps/bumps, and altered sensation.
                        <sup type="ref">[32]</sup> One year after completing 1 to 3 treatment sessions over 6 months, 90% of patients (28/31) with axillary HH had achieved an HDSS score of 1 or 2. Nearly 89% of patients were somewhat satisfied or very satisfied at that point.
                        <sup type="ref">[21]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <em>Endoscopic thoracic sympathectomy </em>is a surgical procedure designed to interrupt the sympathetic signal to the sweat glands. Patient satisfaction rates are higher, and recurrence rates lower, for palmar than axillary HH. Compensatory sweating occurs in more than half of patients and paresthesia in up to half of patients.
                        <sup type="ref">[33]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>6</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Choice of Therapy: Patient Education, Patient-Clinician Dialogue, Shared Decision-Making</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Many patients and their families hold the misconception that HH is not a medical condition and that there is no treatment for it. Only about half (51%) of individuals who self-identified as having HH in an online survey had discussed their symptoms with a healthcare professional.
                        <sup type="ref">[3]</sup> Acknowledging that HH is a real medical condition affecting many people and significantly interfering with personal and professional life can be therapeutic. Educating patients about lifestyle modifications and medical interventions that can improve quality of life can be empowering.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1, Continued</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The clinician reviewed the treatment options with Maya and asked her preference about mode and frequency of administration as well as side effect profile. As Maya wishes to start with the most conservative therapy, they agree to begin with a prescription-strength antiperspirant (20% aluminum chloride hexahydrate). The clinician counsels Maya to apply the antiperspirant at night to completely dry skin, in order to reduce the risk of irritation.
                        <sup type="ref">[1]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Five days later, Maya calls the office describing a painful skin rash at the site of medication application. The clinician instructs her to stop the treatment and return to the office.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Follow-Up Visit #1</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The clinician conducts a detailed review of how Maya was using the antiperspirant. Maya was applying the medication at night after all activities, when she was completely dry. She had not shaved her underarms on the days she used the medication. Therefore, she was deemed intolerant to the treatment.</p>
                    <p>The clinician proposes the recently approved topical glycopyrrolate cloth and off-label topical oxybutynin 10% gel as the next possible options. Maya expresses impatience with topicals and asks about trying an oral anticholinergic agent. The clinician suggests initiation of an oral glycopyrrolate at a dose of 2 mg/day, with optional titration to twice daily after 1 week and 3 times daily after another week if needed for symptom control. In response to the clinician's question, Maya states that she uses birth control and does not plan to become pregnant.</p>
                    <p>Acknowledging that Maya is not impressed with topical interventions, the clinician asks that she consider continuing to use an OTC antiperspirant. Combination therapy may enable symptom control with a lower dose of anticholinergic medication, thus reducing the risk of systemic anticholinergic side effects (eg, dry mouth, dry eyes, constipation, and urinary retention). The patient agrees and decides to go back to applying an OTC 6.25% aluminum chloride product at night. A follow-up visit is scheduled for 2 months, though this can be postponed to 6 months if disease control is adequate.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1, Conclusion</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Maya finds that the oral glycopyrrolate produces symptom control with some occasional, tolerable dry mouth and constipation. She continues to take the oral glycopyrrolate 2 or 3 times daily, depending on situational and seasonal needs, with follow-up every 6 to 12 months.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2, Peter</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table align="left" border="1" bordercolor="#b3b3b3" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" style="margin-right: 20px;">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="center">
                                    <img alt="" border="0" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/258/902258-patient2.jpg?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=200:150" width="200"/>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p style="min-height: 230px;">Peter, a 12-year-old boy, presents to a dermatologist with complaints of severe and spontaneous sweating on his underarms, hands, and feet. His mother, who accompanies Peter to the visit and has seen clinicians in the same dermatology practice, states that she has the same symptoms. After reading about HH, she realizes that new options may be available. She had asked Peter if he would like to see someone in the practice; Peter had indicated a strong preference for seeing the male rather than the female dermatologist.</p>
                    <p>The mother states that Peter has always sweated more than other kids but that this has become more of an issue since Peter's stepmother began to complain about it. Peter's father remarried about a year ago. The parents have joint custody, and Peter spends about 10 days each month with his dad and stepmom. The stepmom complains about the odor of Peter's shoes, socks, and T shirts. Peter becomes very anxious when it is time to go to his dad and stepmom's home.</p>
                    <p>When asked, Peter monosyllabically agrees that he changes his socks and shirt when he arrives home from school, and sometimes changes his socks mid-day for gym class. He says his classmates make fun of his smelly shoes and socks. He stands on the sidelines during most gym activities as he cannot grip a bat or ball. Sometimes he slips when running.</p>
                    <p>The mother states that she sympathizes with Peter's difficulties. A high-strength OTC antiperspirant improved his sweating somewhat in elementary school but symptoms worsened with the onset of puberty.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>7</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Approximately 2.1% of children (&lt;18 years old) have symptoms of HH, according to a US-based online survey in which parents were asked about excessive sweating in their children.
                        <sup type="ref">[3]</sup> The average age of disease onset has been estimated at 14 to 25 years old.
                        <sup type="ref">[34]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2, Continued: History and Physical Examination</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The dermatologist asks Peter and his mother about Peter's history of symptoms and patterns of their occurrence. Peter indicates that excessive heat and humidity and stress worsen symptoms, though symptoms also occur in cool, dry temperatures and calm situations. He sweats on both sides of the body equally, though only on palms of his hands, soles of his feet, and underarms. He has no symptoms during sleep.</p>
                    <p>His mother says that Peter does not wish to attend his middle school dances. She wonders if he is afraid of being mocked for his excess sweating. He says he attended a dance after his stepmom coerced him into going and it was a "disaster." The mother states that Peter socializes less since entering middle school. He does not go to the beach with friends and wears closed-toe shoes in warm weather as he has slipped in flip-flops.</p>
                    <p>Physical examination reveals sweat pooling on the palms, dripping from the feet, and staining the axillary areas of the gown. Peter generally looks at the floor, speaks in a low, barely understandable volume, and does not shake the doctor's hand when it is offered.</p>
                    <p>Although Peter's age of symptom onset and family history of HH support a diagnosis of primary HH, it is important to rule out the most likely causes of secondary HH. Use of relevant medications, as well as risk of endocrine disorders such as diabetes or of lymphoma, can be quickly assessed with a few questions.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Other Clinical Conditions and Use of Medications</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Peter denies experiencing fever, chills, night sweats, or weight loss over the prior year. When asked about other health conditions and medications, the mother indicates that the pediatrician diagnosed Peter with anxiety and prescribed a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) at the well visit about 6 months ago. The pediatrician was concerned about Peter's withdrawn demeanor as well as his apparent self-isolation and lack of self-esteem. Neither Peter nor his mother feel that the medication has helped him.</p>
                    <p>Peter takes no other medication and has no other known illness.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>8</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Anxiety and HH</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Studies report a higher rate of anxiety and depression symptoms in patients with HH compared with patients without the condition (
                        <strong>Figure 4</strong>).
                        <sup type="ref">[35,36]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>
                        <strong>Figure 4. Depression and Anxiety Symptoms Are More Common in Patients With HH*
                            <sup type="ref">[35]</sup>
                        </strong>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/258/902258-fig4.jpg"/>
                    </p>
                    <blockquote>
                        <em>P</em> &lt; .001 for HH vs non-HH, both comparisons

                        <p>* Consecutive dermatology outpatients who completed the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 and the Patient Health Questionnaire-9.</p>
                    </blockquote>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Additionally, SSRIs, including the one that Peter is taking, are known to cause HH (
                        <a href="https://www.sweathelp.org/pdf/drugs_2009.pdf">https://www.sweathelp.org/pdf/drugs_2009.pdf</a>).
                        <sup type="ref">[37]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>The dermatologist explains that the anxiety medication may be exacerbating Peter's sweating symptoms. He suggests working with the pediatrician to stop the drug. Patient and parent agree. The dermatologist communicates to the pediatrician that HH may explain Peter's anxiety and that the SSRI may exacerbate sweating. He suggests stopping the SSRI and refraining from prescribing another antianxiety medication to see if treating the sweating symptoms eases Peter's anxiety.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>HH and Cutaneous Infection</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>HH is associated with an elevated rate of skin infections, including fungal infection and 
                        <em>Verruca plantaris/vulgaris</em>.
                        <sup type="ref">[38]</sup> An examination of Peter's feet, hands, and axillae reveals evidence of a fungal infection on both feet. The dermatologist prescribes a topical antifungal to address this condition.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Assessing PRO</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Asking the patient to complete a PRO measure before and after treatment initiation can document the impact of therapy.
                        <sup type="ref">[39]</sup> The 4-item HDSS (
                        <strong>Figure 2</strong>) asks patients to rate the tolerability of their sweating and the degree to which it interferes with daily activities.
                        <sup type="ref">[28]</sup> However, it does not conform to FDA standards for PRO instruments used to support product labeling. The ASDD includes a 2-item version for children ages 9 to &lt;16 years old.
                        <sup type="ref">[25]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Peter completes the pediatric ASDD before therapy, with a score of 7 out of 10 on question 2, where 10 is "worst possible sweating."</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2, Continued: Patient Education, Patient-Clinician Dialogue, Shared Decision-Making</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Peter is diagnosed with primary axillary, palmar, and plantar HH, possibly aggravated by SSRI therapy. The dermatologist explains to Peter that his sweating is not a variation of normal but a not-uncommon and treatable medical condition. He asks Peter and his mother to consider the office a safe medical environment and to call with any questions or concerns about his sweating.</p>
                    <p>He suggests that Peter change socks midday as well as at gym class and upon returning home from school. He recommends trying flip-flops with a moisture-absorbing footbed.</p>
                    <p>The dermatologist reviews treatment options with Peter and his mother (
                        <strong>Table 2</strong>), eliciting patient and parent concerns and priorities. Peter's mother prefers that he start with topical therapy to maximize safety. Peter is most concerned about efficacy and minimal interference with his routine (eg, not having to apply a topical at school).
                    </p>
                    <p>Peter, his mother and the dermatologist agree to start with a prescription strength antiperspirant (20% aluminum chloride hexahydrate). The dermatologist instructs Peter to assess tolerability by applying the medication to a small area under his left axillae for 1 week to completely dry skin, about 20 minutes before showering. If no rash or irritation develops, then he should apply the medication to all affected areas (palms, soles, and axillae) while in bed, when the skin is completely dry. The dermatologist suggests leaving a towel and the medication at bedside so that Peter can dry off when he gets into bed and then apply the medication while he is in bed. He counsels Peter than no potentially sweat-inducing activities should occur after the medication is applied.</p>
                    <p>A follow-up visit is scheduled for 4 weeks. Peter and his mother are urged to call the office immediately if irritation or rash develops, and anytime with questions or concerns.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>4-Week Follow-Up Visit</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Peter indicates that the antiperspirant helps his hands and feet but does not alleviate his axillary sweating. It also causes some irritation on his underarms. The dermatologist again reviews treatment options and elicits patient and parent concerns and priorities. Peter's mother still prefers a topical to a systemic therapy and expresses concern about treatment side effects. Peter reiterates that he does not want a treatment that he must use at school.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>9</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The patient, mother, and dermatologist agree to try the topical glycopyrrolate cloth, an anticholinergic medication that works differently than the antiperspirant. However, like the antiperspirant, it is noninvasive and used once daily. Peter has no contraindications to this therapy. The dermatologist counsels Peter to use the cloth only on his axillae, as it is FDA approved only for that purpose.
                        <sup type="ref">[27]</sup> The dermatologist suggests that Peter continue using the antiperspirant on his hands and feet, as it relieves symptoms without irritation in those areas. He instructs Peter to use glycopyyrolate cloth when he gets in bed at night, when the skin is clean and completely dry. Peter and his mother agree to try the cloth. The dermatologist explains the most common side effects, including local skin reactions (31%), dry mouth (24%), application site pain (9%), mydriasis (7%), blurred vision (4%), and urinary hesitation (4%) (frequency in clinical trials).
                        <sup type="ref">[15]</sup> He instructs Peter to schedule a follow-up visit for 8 to 12 weeks, and to call if side effects develop or other concerns arise.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Case 2, Conclusion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>At the 8- to 12-week follow-up visit, Peter reports substantial improvement in his palmar, plantar, and axillary sweating. He has experienced no side effects. He tries to keep some of the premoistened topical glycopyrrolate cloths at his dad's house and some at his mom's house so that he need not worry about forgetting to pack them.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>What did you learn from this activity? Please click on the "Next" button to proceed to a brief survey to see how your knowledge improved after the education. You can also see how your answers compare with those of your peers.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content/>
                <qna_form>10</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content/>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label>
            <p>Abbreviations</p>
        </toc_label>
        <toc_type>Sidebar</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Abbreviations</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>ASDD = Axillary Sweating Daily Diary
                        <br/>BMI = body mass index
                        <br/>DLQI = Dermatology Life Quality Index
                        <br/>HDSS = Hyperhidrosis Disease Severity Scale
                        <br/>HH = hyperhidrosis
                        <br/>OTC = over-the-counter
                        <br/>PRO = patient-reported outcome
                        <br/>SSRI = serotonin reuptake inhibitor
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>References</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <ol>
                        <li>Grabell DA, Hebert AA. Current and emerging medical therapies for primary hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Dermatol Ther (Heidelb).</em> 2017;7:25-36.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ricchetti-Masterson K, Symons JM, Aldridge M, et al. Epidemiology of hyperhidrosis in 2 population-based health care databases. 
                            <em>J Am Acad Dermatol.</em> 2018;78:358-362.
                        </li>
                        <li>Doolittle J, Walker P, Mills T, Thurston J. Hyperhidrosis: an update on prevalence and severity in the United States. 
                            <em>Arch Dermatol Res</em>. 2016;308:743-749.
                        </li>
                        <li>Moraites E, Vaughn OA, Hill S. Incidence and prevalence of hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Dermatol Clin</em>. 2014;32:457-465.
                        </li>
                        <li>Walling HW. Clinical differentiation of primary from secondary hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>J Am Acad Dermatol</em>. 2011;64:690-695.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ro KM, Cantor RM, Lange KL, Ahn SS. Palmar hyperhidrosis: evidence of genetic transmission
                            <em>. J Vasc Surg</em>. 2002;35:382-386.
                        </li>
                        <li>Kaufmann H, Saadia D, Polin C, Hague S, Singleton A, Singleton A. Primary hyperhidrosis--evidence for autosomal dominant inheritance. 
                            <em>Clin Auton Res</em>. 2003;13:96-98.
                        </li>
                        <li>Singh S, Davis H, Wilson P. Axillary hyperhidrosis: a review of the extent of the problem and treatment modalities. 
                            <em>Surgeon</em>. 2015;13:279-285.
                        </li>
                        <li>de Moura Junior NB, das-Neves-Pereira JC, de Oliveira FR, et al. Expression of acetylcholine and its receptor in human sympathetic ganglia in primary hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Ann Thorac Surg</em>. 2013;95:465-470.
                        </li>
                        <li>Licht PB. Invited commentary. 
                            <em>Ann Thorac Surg</em>. 2013;95:470-471.
                        </li>
                        <li>Hamm H, Naumann MK, Kowalski JW, Kutt S, Kozma C, Teale C. Primary focal hyperhidrosis: disease characteristics and functional impairment. 
                            <em>Dermatology</em>. 2006;212:343-353.
                        </li>
                        <li>Kamudoni P, Mueller B, Halford J, Schouveller A, Stacey B, Salek MS. The impact of hyperhidrosis on patients' daily life and quality of life: a qualitative investigation. 
                            <em>Health Qual Life Outcomes</em>. 2017;15:121.
                        </li>
                        <li>Liu Y, Bahar R, Kalia S, et al. Hyperhidrosis prevalence and demographical characteristics in dermatology outpatients in Shanghai and Vancouver. 
                            <em>PLoS One</em>. 2016;11:e0153719.
                        </li>
                        <li>Mirmirani P, Carpenter DM. Skin disorders associated with obesity in children and adolescents: a population-based study. 
                            <em>Pediatr Dermatol</em>. 2014;31:183-190.
                        </li>
                        <li>Glaser DA, Hebert AA, Nast A, et al. Topical glycopyrronium tosylate for the treatment of primary axillary hyperhidrosis: Results from the ATMOS-1 and ATMOS-2 phase 3 randomized controlled trials. 
                            <em>J Am Acad Dermatol</em>. 2018. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2018.07.002. [Epub ahead of print]
                        </li>
                        <li>Artzi O, Loizides C, Zur E, Sprecher E. Topical oxybutynin 10% gel for the treatment of primary focal hyperhidrosis: a randomized double-blind placebo-controlled split area study. 
                            <em>Acta Derm Venereol</em>. 2017;97:1120-1124.
                        </li>
                        <li>Cruddas L, Baker DM. Treatment of primary hyperhidrosis with oral anticholinergic medications: a systematic review. 
                            <em>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</em>. 2017;31:952-963.
                        </li>
                        <li>Walling HW. Systemic therapy for primary hyperhidrosis: a retrospective study of 59 patients treated with glycopyrrolate or clonidine. 
                            <em>J Am Acad Dermatol</em>. 2012;66:387-392.
                        </li>
                        <li>Naumann M, Lowe NJ. Botulinum toxin type A in treatment of bilateral primary axillary hyperhidrosis: randomised, parallel group, double blind, placebo controlled trial. 
                            <em>BMJ</em>. 2001;323:596-599.
                        </li>
                        <li>Kim DH, Kim TH, Lee SH, Lee AY. Treatment of palmar hyperhidrosis with tap water iontophoresis: a randomized, sham-controlled, single-blind, and parallel-designed clinical trial. 
                            <em>Ann Dermatol</em>. 2017;29:728-734.
                        </li>
                        <li>Hong HC, Lupin M, O'Shaughnessy KF. Clinical evaluation of a microwave device for treating axillary hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Dermatol Surg</em>. 2012;38:728-735.
                        </li>
                        <li>Scholes KT, Crow KD, Ellis JP, Harman RR, Saihan EM. Axillary hyperhidrosis treated with alcoholic solution of aluminium chloride hexahydrate. 
                            <em>Br Med J.</em> 1978(6130):84-85.
                        </li>
                        <li>Goh CL. Aluminum chloride hexahydrate versus palmar hyperhidrosis. Evaporimeter assessment. 
                            <em>Int J Dermatol.</em> 1990;29:368-370.
                        </li>
                        <li>Streker M, Reuther T, Hagen L, Kerscher M. Hyperhidrosis plantaris - a randomized, half-side trial for efficacy and safety of an antiperspirant containing different concentrations of aluminium chloride. 
                            <em>J Dtsch Dermatol Ges</em>. 2012;10:115-119.
                        </li>
                        <li>Glaser DA, Hebert AA, Fehnel S, et al. Confirmatory psychometric evaluation of the Axillary Sweating Daily Diary: A validated patient-reported outcome measure to assess axillary hyperhidrosis sweating severity. Presented at: 36th Fall Clinical Dermatology Conference; October 12-15, 2017; Las Vegas, NV.</li>
                        <li>Glaser DA, Hebert AA, Nast A, Werschler WP, et al. Open-label study (ARIDO) evaluating long-term safety of topical glycopyrronium tosylate (GT) in patients with primary axillary hyperhidrosis. Presented at: 36th Fall Clinical Dermatology Conference; October 12-15, 2017; Las Vegas NV.</li>
                        <li>Qbrexza™ [package insert]. Menlo Park, CA: Dermira; 2018.</li>
                        <li>Solish N, Bertucci V, Dansereau A, et al. A comprehensive approach to the recognition, diagnosis, and severity-based treatment of focal hyperhidrosis: recommendations of the Canadian Hyperhidrosis Advisory Committee. 
                            <em>Dermatol Surg</em>. 2007;33:908-923.
                        </li>
                        <li>Naumann M, Lowe NJ, Kumar CR, Hamm H. Botulinum toxin type a is a safe and effective treatment for axillary hyperhidrosis over 16 months: a prospective study. 
                            <em>Arch Dermatol</em>. 2003;139:731-736.
                        </li>
                        <li>Schieman C, Gelfand GJ, Grondin SC. Hyperhidrosis: clinical presentation, evaluation and management. 
                            <em>Expert Review of Dermatology</em>. 2010;5:31-44.
                        </li>
                        <li>Pariser DM, Ballard A. Iontophoresis for palmar and plantar hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Dermatol Clin.</em> 2014;32:491-494.
                        </li>
                        <li>Jacob C. Treatment of hyperhidrosis with microwave technology. 
                            <em>Semin Cutan Med Surg</em>. 2013;32:2-8.
                        </li>
                        <li>Moraites E, Vaughn OA, Hill S. Endoscopic thoracic sympathectomy. 
                            <em>Dermatol Clin.</em> 2014;32:541-548.
                        </li>
                        <li>Bohaty BR, Hebert AA. Special considerations for children with hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Dermatol Clin.</em> 2014;32:477-484.
                        </li>
                        <li>Bahar R, Zhou P, Liu Y, et al. The prevalence of anxiety and depression in patients with or without hyperhidrosis (HH). 
                            <em>J Am Acad Dermatol</em>. 2016;75:1126-1133.
                        </li>
                        <li>Gross KM, Schote AB, Schneider KK, Schulz A, Meyer J. Elevated social stress levels and depressive symptoms in primary hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>PLoS One</em>. 2014;9:e92412.
                        </li>
                        <li>Zoloft® [package insert]. New York, NY: Pfizer, Inc.; 2018.</li>
                        <li>Walling HW. Primary hyperhidrosis increases the risk of cutaneous infection: a case-control study of 387 patients. 
                            <em>J Am Acad Dermatol</em>. 2009;61:242-246.
                        </li>
                        <li>Stashak AB, Brewer JD. Management of hyperhidrosis. 
                            <em>Clin Cosmet Investig Dermatol</em>. 2014;7:285-299.
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <back_label>Back Matter</back_label>
    <layer_grp>
        <layer_img_sm/>
        <layer_img_full/>
        <layer_caption/>
        <layer_label/>
        <layer_alt_txt/>
        <layer_table/>
    </layer_grp>
    <ref_grp>
        <ref_item/>
    </ref_grp>
    <cpyrt_holder>
        <p>Medscape, LLC</p>
    </cpyrt_holder>
    <cpyrt_ovrd/>
    <disclmr_ovrd/>
    <bkmtr_front>
        <p>
            <strong>Disclaimer</strong>
        </p>
        <p>The educational activity presented above may involve simulated case-based scenarios. The patients depicted in these scenarios are fictitious and no association with any actual patient is intended or should be inferred.</p>
        <p>The material presented here does not necessarily reflect the views of Medscape, LLC, or companies that support educational programming on medscape.org. These materials may discuss therapeutic products that have not been approved by the US Food and Drug Administration and off-label uses of approved products. A qualified healthcare professional should be consulted before using any therapeutic product discussed. Readers should verify all information and data before treating patients or employing any therapies described in this educational activity.</p>
    </bkmtr_front>
    <bkmtr_glossary/>
    <bkmtr_ack/>
    <bkmtr_discl/>
    <bkmtr_funding/>
    <bkmtr_reprnt_addr/>
    <bkmtr_abbr_notes/>
    <bkmtr_last/>
    <img_ttl_bkgrd>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/title_background/banner-hyperhidrosis.jpg</img_ttl_bkgrd>
    <img_publ_logo/>
</prof_article>
