<prof_article_slide_presentation>
  <front_label>Front Matter</front_label>
  <above_title>
    <p>
      <a href="/sites/advances/psoriasis-mgmt">CLINICAL ADVANCES IN PSORIASIS: The Path Toward Clear Skin</a>
    </p>
  </above_title>
  <title>
    <p>Are You a Psoriasis Expert? Patient Case Challenge</p>
  </title>
  <contrbtr_pre_content>
    <p>As an organization accredited by the ACCME, Medscape, LLC, requires everyone who is in a position to control the content of an education activity to disclose all relevant financial relationships with any commercial interest.  The ACCME defines "relevant financial relationships" as financial relationships in any amount, occurring within the past 12 months, including financial relationships of a spouse or life partner, that could create a conflict of interest.</p>
<p>Medscape, LLC, encourages Authors to identify investigational products or off-label uses of products regulated by the US Food and Drug Administration, at first mention and where appropriate in the content.</p>
  </contrbtr_pre_content>
  <contrbtr_byline>
    <p>Jeffrey J. Crowley, MD</p>
  </contrbtr_byline>
  <contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_type_lbl>Faculty</contrbtr_type_lbl>
    <contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c791808aea2e">
      <contrbtr_nm>Jeffrey J. Crowley, MD</contrbtr_nm>
      <contrbtr_title>
        <p>Dermatologist, Bakersfield Dermatology, Bakersfield, California</p>
      </contrbtr_title>
      <contrbtr_bio/>
      <contrbtr_disclsr>
        <p>Disclosure: Jeffrey J. Crowley, MD, has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships:<br/>Served as an advisor or consultant for: AbbVie Inc.; Amgen Inc.; Celgene Corporation; Janssen Pharmaceuticals; Lilly; Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation; Sun Pharmaceutical Industries, Ltd.; UCB Pharma, Inc.<br/>Served as a speaker or a member of a speakers bureau for: AbbVie Inc.; Amgen Inc.; Janssen Pharmaceuticals; Lilly; Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation; Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Sanofi-Aventis<br/>Received grants for clinical research from: AbbVie Inc.; Amgen Inc.; Celgene Corporation; Janssen Pharmaceuticals; Lilly; MC2 Therapeutics; Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation; Regeneron Pharmaceuticals, Inc.; Sanofi-Aventis; UCB Pharma, Inc.; Verrica Pharmaceuticals<br/>
<br/>Dr Crowley does intend to discuss off-label uses of drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics approved by the FDA for use in the United States.<br/>
<br/>Dr Crowley does intend to discuss investigational drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics not approved by the FDA for use in the United States.</p>
      </contrbtr_disclsr>
    </contrbtr_element>
  </contrbtr_group>
  <contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_type_lbl>Editors</contrbtr_type_lbl>
    <contrbtr_element>
      <contrbtr_nm>Shari J. Dermer, PhD</contrbtr_nm>
      <contrbtr_title>
        <p>Scientific Director, Medscape, LLC</p>
      </contrbtr_title>
      <contrbtr_bio/>
      <contrbtr_disclsr>
        <p>Disclosure: Shari J. Dermer, PhD has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
      </contrbtr_disclsr>
    </contrbtr_element>
    <contrbtr_element>
      <contrbtr_nm>Megan M. Stephan, PhD</contrbtr_nm>
      <contrbtr_title>
        <p>Medical Writer, Somerville, MA</p>
      </contrbtr_title>
      <contrbtr_bio/>
      <contrbtr_disclsr>
        <p>Disclosure: Megan M. Stephan, PhD has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
      </contrbtr_disclsr>
    </contrbtr_element>
  </contrbtr_group>
  <contrbtr_bulk_info/>
  <contrbtr_post_content>
    <p>
<strong>Peer Reviewer</strong>
</p>
<p>This activity has been peer reviewed and the reviewer has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
  </contrbtr_post_content>
  <supprtr_grant_group>
    <supprtr_grant_attr>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/grant_attribution/ortho_dermatologics-valeant-pharmaceuticals-ieg-txt-2017.gif</supprtr_grant_attr>
  </supprtr_grant_group>
  <body_label>Body</body_label>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>The following cases are modeled on the interactive grand rounds approach. The questions within the activity are designed to test your current knowledge. After each question, you will be able to see whether you answered correctly and read evidence-based information that supports the most appropriate answer choice. The questions are designed to challenge you; you will not be penalized for answering the questions incorrectly. At the end of the activity, there will be a short post-test assessment based on the material presented.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Assess your clinical knowledge by completing this brief survey. Answering these questions again after the activity will allow you to see what you learned and to compare your answers with those of your peers.</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>3</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <pg_footnotes/>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 1: Patient History</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <table align="left" border="1" bordercolor="#b3b3b3" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" style="margin-right: 20px;">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td align="center">
<img alt="" border="0" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/894/123/894123-patient1.jpg?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=200:150" width="200"/>
</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>

<p>Jessica is a 24-year-old woman who comes to your office because of concerns about the appearance of her skin. She has patches of red, dry, itchy skin on her knees and elbows that make her embarrassed to wear shorts or short-sleeved shirts. She says her scalp itches as well and appears to be flaking. On physical examination, you note:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Large, well-defined, raised erythematous lesions with overlying silvery scale on the extensor surfaces of her knees and elbows</li>
    <li>Scale and some hair loss on her scalp, with visible red patches of skin along the hairline</li>
</ul>

<p>You estimate that all together these lesions cover about 2% of her body surface area (BSA).</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Figure 1. Mild to Moderate Plaque Psoriasis Lesions of the Scalp</strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>
<em>This image is no longer available</em>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>4</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Diagnosis and Evaluation of Psoriasis</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Psoriasis is a chronic, systemic inflammatory condition that manifests primarily as a skin and joint disorder.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> As shown in Table 1, there are multiple types of psoriasis, including plaque, inverse (or intertriginous), erythrodermic, pustular, and guttate. Plaque psoriasis is the most common type, occurring in 80% to 90% of patients. Many patients with psoriasis have more than 1 type. Although the less common types of psoriasis are frequently excluded from clinical trials, they can have a high impact on patient QoL, and should be considered when evaluating disease severity. In addition to their effects on appearance, active psoriatic lesions can cause considerable patient distress because of pruritus and pain.<sup type="ref">[1,2]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Table 1. Types of Psoriasis<sup type="ref">[1,2]</sup> </strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <table class="inline_data_table">
    <tbody>
        <tr valign="top">
            <th>Type</th>
            <th>Locations</th>
            <th>Appearance</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Plaque</td>
            <td>Scalp, trunk, buttocks, extensor surfaces of limbs</td>
            <td>Irregular, round to oval, well-defined, sharply demarcated plaques<br/>Dry, thin silvery overlying scale</td>
            <td>Tends to be symmetrically distributed</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Inverse (intertriginous)</td>
            <td>Axillary, genital, perineal, intergluteal, inframammary, antecubital fossae, and below the pannus</td>
            <td>Thin erythematous plaques with minimal scale that may cover an entire body surface</td>
            <td>Involvement of thinner, more sensitive areas of skin necessitates caution with high-potency topical steroids</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Erythrodermic</td>
            <td>Entire body surface (over 80% of body)</td>
            <td>Generalized erythema with varying degrees of scaling</td>
            <td>Often accompanied by fever, chills, hypothermia, dehydration, malaise</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Pustular</td>
            <td>Generalized or localized; one variant involves palms and soles only</td>
            <td>Widespread pustules on an erythematous background<br/>May be present with psoriasis vulgaris</td>
            <td>May be severe and accompanied by fever and toxicity</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Guttate</td>
            <td>Trunk and proximal extremities</td>
            <td>Small (5 mm to 20 mm) pink papules and plaques with fine scale</td>
            <td>Often preceded by upper respiratory tract infection with group A beta-hemolytic streptococci</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Diagnosis of psoriasis is primarily made on the basis of patient history and physical examination. Types of psoriasis can be differentiated from one another based on lesion location and morphology.<sup type="ref">[2]</sup> Psoriasis is usually, but not always, symmetric. In addition to the trunk, buttocks, and extremities, the scalp, ears, nails, and anogenital region should be examined. Patient history taking should include questions about joint pain and stiffness that can indicate the presence of psoriatic arthritis, a common comorbidity in more severe, longstanding cases.<sup type="ref">[3]</sup> Questions about family history may also be germane because about 45% of patients indicate a family history of psoriasis.<sup type="ref">[4]</sup>
</p>
<p>Differential diagnoses for psoriasis, which are shown in Table 2, include common skin disorders, infectious conditions, and neoplastic conditions. If there is any doubt, a skin biopsy can be used to detect fungal or bacterial infection or the presence of a malignancy.<sup type="ref">[2,3]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Table 2. Differential Diagnoses for Psoriasis<sup type="ref">[2,3]</sup> </strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <table class="inline_data_table">
    <tbody>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="5">
<strong>Common skin conditions</strong>
</td>
            <td>Atopic dermatitis</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Contact dermatitis</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Lichen planus</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Seborrheic dermatitis</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Pityriasis rosea</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="2">
<strong>Infectious skin conditions</strong>
</td>
            <td>Tinea corporis</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Secondary syphilis</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="2">
<strong>Neoplastic skin conditions</strong>
</td>
            <td>Squamous cell carcinoma</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Mycosis fungoides (cutaneous T-cell lymphoma)</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Evaluation of psoriasis as mild, moderate, or severe plays an important role in therapeutic decision-making. Factors to consider include percent of BSA involvement, lesion location and thickness, and the presence or absence of psoriatic arthritis. Symptom burden, psychosocial factors, and effects on QoL also should be considered. Although it is rarely used in clinical practice, clinicians should be aware of the Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI), an assessment scheme that is often used in clinical trials. This measure includes assessment of erythema, plaque thickness, and scaling as well as percent of BSA covered in 4 body areas (Figure 2). The percentage of patients whose PASI score is reduced by 75% (PASI75) is often used as an endpoint and as a means of comparing efficacy rates across clinical trials. Disease severity is also sometimes assessed with a Physicians Global Assessment (PGA) or Investigators Global Assessment (IGA), in which researchers assign a single point value from clear (0) to most severe, usually on a 5-point or 7-point scale.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Figure 2. Body Areas Evaluated in PASI</strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>
<img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/894/123/894123-fig2.png"/>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>5</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Symptom Burden and QoL Impacts in Patients With Psoriasis</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Psoriasis most often appears in patients during their early 20s, which can have a significant impact on their lives and lead to social isolation, changes in career choices, and difficulties with work.</p>
<p>Psoriasis and its symptoms can be quite detrimental to patients' QoL. Physical symptoms of psoriasis include erythema, scaling and flaking, pruritus, and skin and/or joint pain.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> Pruritus, usually moderate to severe, occurs in 36% to 41% of patients.<sup type="ref">[5,6]</sup> Skin pain is less common, affecting 17% of patients. Both symptoms are associated with worsening of QoL.<sup type="ref">[5]</sup> Although the vast majority of clinicians cite location and size of lesions as the most important factor contributing to disease severity, patients with psoriasis indicate that pruritus is the most important factor, followed by location and size of lesions, scaling, and flaking. In patients who also have psoriatic arthritis, pain and swelling of joints overtakes all of these factors as the most important consideration.<sup type="ref">[6]</sup>
</p>
<p>About three-quarters of patients with psoriasis report at least 1 comorbidity, which can reduce patient QoL even further (see <em>Medical Comorbidities of Psoriasis</em>).<sup type="ref">[5,6]</sup> These often include psychological comorbidities such as anxiety and depression, low self-esteem, and high stress levels.<sup type="ref">[4-7]</sup> Patients may experience sleeplessness and fatigue as a result of pruritus.<sup type="ref">[5]</sup> Many patients report excessive alcohol use and smoking.<sup type="ref">[4,5,7]</sup> Psoriasis and its comorbidities can lead to social isolation, loss of work productivity, family difficulties, and suicidal ideation.<sup type="ref">[1,5]</sup> Patients whose psoriasis is in visible and non-visible body areas have reduced QoL compared with those whose lesions are only in non-visible areas, suggesting that patient distress and resulting loss of QoL are at least partly linked to concerns about appearance.<sup type="ref">[5]</sup>
</p>
<p>Overall, psoriasis is a chronic condition in which symptoms and comorbidities require lifelong management. In addition to clinical assessment of disease severity, clinicians should be prepared to assess psychological and medical comorbidities and take these factors into account when selecting therapies for these patients.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 1 (Cont): Symptom Evaluation</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Based on the appearance of her lesions and her symptoms, you diagnose Jessica with plaque psoriasis. During the examination, Jessica states that she is reluctant to date or go out in social settings. She complains about fractured sleep and daytime sleepiness due to pruritus that keeps her up at night. Although the physical presentation of Jessica's psoriasis would be considered mild, the symptoms of pruritus, sleep disturbance, social anxiety, and psychological distress that she describes lead you to consider her psoriasis as mild to moderate. You explain to Jessica that psoriasis is a lifelong condition, but that effective therapies are available. Because she has already tried using moisturizers, you discuss starting her on prescription topical medication(s).</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>6</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Psoriasis Treatment: Topical Agents</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Guidelines from the American Academy of Dermatology (AAD), recommend topical therapies alone for first-line treatment of mild to moderate psoriasis, although systemic therapy or phototherapy can also be initiated in patients whose psoriasis has a high QoL impact.<sup type="ref">[8] </sup>Topical agents are also used as adjunctive therapies in patients with moderate to severe disease.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Table 3 shows classes of prescription topical therapies that are available for psoriasis in the United States and some of their characteristics.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Table 3. Classes of Topical Psoriasis Therapies<sup type="ref">[8,9]</sup> </strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <table class="inline_data_table">
    <tbody>
        <tr valign="top">
            <th>Class</th>
            <th>Examples</th>
            <th>Efficacy</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Corticosteroids</td>
            <td>Numerous with a wide range of potencies (see Table 4)</td>
            <td>Considered the gold standard<br/>Class I and class II have the highest efficacy</td>
            <td>Higher potencies not recommended for prolonged use or for the face and other areas where skin is thin</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Vitamin D analogues</td>
            <td>Calcipotriene, calcitriol</td>
            <td>Higher remission rates than corticosteroids but slower onset</td>
            <td>More likely to cause skin irritation than topical corticosteroids</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Retinoids</td>
            <td>Tazarotene</td>
            <td>Moderate efficacy</td>
            <td>Contraindicated in pregnant women<br/>Associated with photosensitivity and irritation</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Calcineurin inhibitors (off-label)</td>
            <td>Tacrolimus,<br/>pimecrolimus</td>
            <td>Moderate efficacy</td>
            <td>Can be used on face (away from eyes), and on flexural and genital areas</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Corticosteroids</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Corticosteroids are the mainstay of topical treatment of psoriasis because of their anti-inflammatory, anti-proliferative, immunosuppressive, and vasoconstrictive effects.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Topical corticosteroids vary by potency from lowest (class VII) to very high (class I), with potency dependent on agent, concentration, and formulation.<sup type="ref">[10]</sup> As shown in Table 4, there are many available concentrations and formulations, which allows for tailoring to disease severity, lesion thickness and location, and patient age and preferences.<sup type="ref">[8,10]</sup> Type of formulation can affect the potency of corticosteroids; for example, betamethasone dipropionate 0.05% ointment is a class II agent whereas betamethasone dipropionate 0.05% cream is a class III agent.<sup type="ref">[10]</sup>
</p>
<p>Data from randomized controlled trials (RCTs) show that most topical corticosteroids are better than placebo at reducing psoriasis severity, with higher efficacy rates for the most potent agents.<sup type="ref">[8,11]</sup> Although well-tolerated, prolonged use of topical corticosteroids can be associated with skin reactions, including cutaneous atrophy, telangiectasia, hypopigmentation, and striae. Side effects can be managed with pulse therapy regimens (weekend use only of corticosteroids alternating with vitamin D analogues) or step-down therapy with a less potent treatment after control has been achieved.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>Cutaneous atrophy can cause subclinical skin barrier disruption, leading to the potential for systemic adverse effects related to hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis (HPA) suppression, such as adrenal suppression and insufficiency, Cushing syndrome, hyperglycemia, and hypertension.<sup type="ref">[10]</sup> Risk of systemic side effects is highest with high- or ultra-high-potency agents, but HPA suppression has been observed with widespread, extended use of mid-potency agents as well. AAD guidelines recommend that use of class I topical corticosteroids be limited to no more than twice daily for 2 to 4 weeks and no more than 50 g per week.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Table 4. Topical Corticosteroids<sup type="ref">[8,9]</sup> </strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <table class="inline_data_table">
    <tbody>
        <tr valign="top">
            <th>Class</th>
            <th>Agent</th>
            <th>Formulations</th>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="3">Class I: very high potency</td>
            <td>Clobetasol propionate</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, gel</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Fluocinonide</td>
            <td>0.1% cream</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Halobetasol propionate</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, ointment</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="3">Class II: high potency</td>
            <td>Betamethasone dipropionate</td>
            <td>0.05% ointment</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Fluocinonide</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, gel, ointment, solution</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Triamcinolone acetonide</td>
            <td>0.5% ointment</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="9">Class III-IV: medium potency</td>
            <td>Betamethasone dipropionate</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, lotion</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Betamethasone valerate</td>
            <td>0.1% cream, ointment, lotion<br/>0.12% foam</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Clocortolone pivalate</td>
            <td>0.1% cream</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Desoximetasone</td>
            <td>0.05% cream</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Fluocinonide</td>
            <td>0.05% cream</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Fluticasone propionate</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, ointment, lotion</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Hydrocortisone valerate</td>
            <td>0.2% cream, ointment</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Mometasone furoate</td>
            <td>0.01% cream, ointment, lotion</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Triamcinolone acetonide</td>
            <td>0.025% cream, lotion, ointment<br/>0.147% spray<br/>0.1% lotion</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="5">Class V-VII: low potency</td>
            <td>Alclometasone dipropionate</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, ointment</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Desonide</td>
            <td>0.05% cream, ointment, lotion</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Fluocinolone acetonide</td>
            <td>0.01% cream, oil, shampoo, solution</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Hydrocortisone OTC</td>
            <td>0.5% cream</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Hydrocortisone</td>
            <td>1% cream, ointment<br/>2.5% cream, ointment, lotion</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>

<blockquote>OTC = over the counter.</blockquote>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Vitamin D Analogues</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Vitamin D analogues inhibit keratinocyte proliferation, enhance keratinocyte differentiation, and reduce inflammation, reversing cellular changes caused by psoriasis.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Vitamin D analogues that are currently available in the United States include calcipotriene 0.005% cream, ointment, solution, and foam; and calcitriol 3 µg/g ointment.<sup type="ref">[9]</sup> RCTs have shown that vitamin D analogues are significantly more effective than placebo.<sup type="ref">[11,12]</sup> Calcipotriene in particular is as effective as very potent topical corticosteroids in treating mild to moderate chronic plaque psoriasis, and superior to calcitriol, coal tar, and short-contact anthralin. Vitamin D analogues can be used as monotherapies or in combination with topical corticosteroids (see <em>Topical</em> <em>Combination Therapy</em>).<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>Although mild and well-tolerated, calcipotriene can cause transient skin irritation at the site of application, including pruritus and burning pain.<sup type="ref">[12]</sup> Calcitriol has similar but milder side effects. Calcitriol is degraded by acidic therapies, such as salicylic acid, and by ultraviolet light. Patients should be warned that sun exposure may inactivate this therapy and to be careful about the timing of other topical therapies and phototherapy. Vitamin D analogues are associated with rare instances of hypercalcemia and hypercalciuria but no monitoring is necessary with their use.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Topical Combination Therapy</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Topical corticosteroid/vitamin D analogue combination therapy reduces the risk of cutaneous atrophy associated with corticosteroids, reduces skin irritation associated with vitamin D analogues, and enhances the activity of both agents compared with the monotherapies alone.<sup type="ref">[8,13]</sup> These considerations led to the development of calcipotriene 0.005%/betamethasone dipropionate 0.064% ointment, gel, and foam formulations, with the aim of simplifying and improving adherence to combination therapy.<sup type="ref">[13]</sup> The topical suspension is approved for treatment of plaque psoriasis of the scalp and body in patients aged 18 years and older, and plaque psoriasis of the scalp in patients aged 12 to 17 years. The most common adverse reactions are folliculitis and burning pain. Rare serious adverse events (AEs) reflect those of the 2 active agents (ie, hypercalcemia or hypercalciuria and reversible HPA axis suppression).<sup type="ref">[14]</sup>
</p>
<p>The foam formulation was approved in 2015 on the basis of the phase 3 PSO-FAST trial, which randomized adult patients with psoriasis to the active combination or foam vehicle. At week 4, 53.3% of patients treated with the active combination showed treatment success by PGA compared with 4.8% of patients treated with vehicle alone.<sup type="ref">[15]</sup> This formulation is approved for topical treatment of plaque psoriasis in patients aged 18 years and older. Adverse reactions reported in less than 1% of patients include application site irritation and/or pruritus, folliculitis, skin hypopigmentation, hypercalcemia, urticaria, and exacerbation of psoriasis. Rare serious AEs are the same as those for the gel formulation.<sup type="ref">[16]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Tazarotene</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Tazarotene is a vitamin A derivative (retinoid) that is thought to normalize abnormal keratinocyte differentiation, reduce keratinocyte hyperproliferation, and reduce inflammation. RCTs show moderate efficacy in psoriasis. Common adverse reactions include lesional and perilesional skin irritation (pruritus, burning/stinging, erythema) and photosensitization. Irritation can be reduced by using a lower concentration or cream formulation, applying on alternate days, short-contact use, and applying in combination with topical corticosteroids.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> A fixed-combination topical tazarotene/corticosteroid therapy is currently in clinical trials (see <em>New and Emerging Topical Therapies</em>).</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Additional Topical Therapies</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>
<strong>Anthralin.</strong> Anthralin (dithranol) was once a mainstay of psoriasis treatment that is used less often now with the availability of better tolerated, more effective agents. Limited clinical evidence suggests that this agent is less efficacious than more potent topical corticosteroids or vitamin D analogues. Anthralin is used only as a short-contact agent and is not recommended for the face or intertriginous areas because of the potential for severe skin irritation. Anthralin is also associated with staining of lesions, skin, nails, clothing, and other objects.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Calcineurin Inhibitors.</strong>The topical calcineurin inhibitors tacrolimus and pimecrolimus are US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved for treating atopic dermatitis and are sometimes used off-label for psoriasis. These agents have shown moderate efficacy for treating facial and intertriginous psoriasis, but do not appear to penetrate thicker lesions well enough to treat plaques. Common AEs include transient burning and itching, which can be mitigated by not applying immediately after bathing. Both agents carry a boxed warning for potential risk of malignancy, although a causal link has not been identified.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Coal tar. </strong>Coal tar is a distillation product of coal that is also used less often now with the availability of better tolerated, more effective agents. Coal tar is associated with cosmetic issues, including staining of clothes and odor, and adverse effects, which include irritant contact dermatitis, folliculitis, and photosensitivity.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Salicylic acid.</strong> Salicylic acid is a keratolytic agent that appears to enhance the activity of other topical therapies for psoriasis by improving skin penetration. Salicylic acid should not be used in combination with systemic salicylate therapies or with ultraviolet B (UVB) phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Considerations for Women of Childbearing Age</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Clinicians should discuss risks, benefits, and appropriate precautions when prescribing topical treatments for psoriasis for women of childbearing age. Most topical therapies for psoriasis have not been tested in pregnant women and in most cases it is unknown if they are excreted in breast milk. Tazarotene, a retinoid, is absolutely contraindicated in women who are or may become pregnant because of its teratogenic effects. Treatments that are considered safest for pregnant women include emollients, salicylic acid, and brief use of coal tar products.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>Topical corticosteroids have received limited study in pregnancy. A 2011 population-based cohort study that compared pregnancy outcomes in 35,503 women who were prescribed topical corticosteroids during the period from 85 days before their last menstrual period to delivery or fetal death with those of 48,630 unexposed women found no difference in risks for orofacial cleft, preterm delivery, miscarriage, or stillbirth. However, exposure to potent or very potent topical corticosteroids shortly before or during pregnancy was associated with a 2-fold higher risk of fetal growth restriction.<sup type="ref">[17]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>New and Emerging Topical Therapies</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Recent clinical trials have investigated new fixed combinations of existing agents for psoriasis as well as topical agents with novel mechanisms.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Halobetasol/Tazarotene Fixed Combination</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Several lines of evidence suggest that combining tazarotene with a topical corticosteroid may have synergistic effects that improve efficacy and reduce adverse effects compared with either agent alone, and that may allow use of a lower steroid concentration.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> A fixed-dose topical combination, halobetasol propionate 0.01%/tazarotene 0.045% lotion, is in clinical trials for moderate to severe plaque psoriasis. Data from 2 phase 3 studies with a total of 418 patients were recently published. A significantly greater percentage of patients in the halobetasol propionate/tazarotene groups demonstrated a 2-grade improvement and clear or almost clear in the IGA (36% and 45%) compared with patients in the vehicle groups (7% and 12%; <em>P </em>&lt;.001 for both comparisons).<sup type="ref">[18]</sup> The most common adverse effects were application site reactions (pain, pruritus, and erythema). Very few patients experienced adverse skin reactions, such as atrophy, striae, telangiectasia, and folliculitis, which are typical of topical corticosteroids.<sup type="ref">[18]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Janus Kinase Inhibitors</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Janus kinase (JAK) inhibitors are of interest in psoriasis because of their abilities to block interleukin (IL) activities involved in inflammation and hyperkeratinization. A phase 2B trial investigated the effects of tofacitinib, a small-molecule JAK1/3 inhibitor, on psoriasis severity and patient-reported outcomes including the Itch Severity Item (ISI) and the Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI).<sup type="ref">[19]</sup>A total of 435 patients with mild to moderate psoriasis were randomized to once- or twice-daily treatment with 2% tofacitinib ointment, 1% tofacitinib ointment, or vehicle alone. Patients treated with 2% tofacitinib showed significant improvements in PGA of clear or almost clear and at least a 2-grade improvement at week 8 but not week 12, together with significant improvements in ISI and DLQI, which were maintained at 12 weeks. Treatment-emergent AEs were mostly mild or moderate with no clinically meaningful differences between the tofacitinib and vehicle treatment groups.<sup type="ref">[19]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Pegcantratinib (SNA-120, CT327)</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Increased cutaneous signaling through nerve growth factor/tropomyosin receptor kinase A (TrkA)/transient receptor potential cation channel V1 pathways is thought to play a key role in chronic pruritus associated with dermatologic conditions, including psoriasis. CT327 is a selective TrkA inhibitor that is currently in phase 2 trials for pruritus associated with psoriasis. A phase 2b study in 153 patients with psoriasis found statistically significant reductions in pruritus in the subpopulation of patients with at least moderate pruritus at baseline (about 70% of the total population) as measured by patient rating on a visual analogue scale (VAS).<sup type="ref">[20]</sup> About 60% of patients using the 0.05% CT327 formulation had at least a 50% reduction in pruritus VAS compared with 32% on vehicle (an emollient). CT327 was well-tolerated with no reported application site reactions and no treatment-related serious AEs.<sup type="ref">[20]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>7</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Considerations for Topical Treatment Selection</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Selection of topical therapies should be tailored to individual patients' disease characteristics, treatment goals, and preferences. Disease characteristics to consider include type of psoriasis and body location, lesion thickness, degree of erythema, and amount of scaling. Medium- to high-potency corticosteroids are recommended in adult patients for thicker plaques. Lower-potency corticosteroids can be used for limited time periods on the face, intertriginous areas, and other areas where the skin is thin.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
<p>Among vitamin D analogues, calcitriol is better tolerated on the face than calcipotriene.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Use of calcipotriene/betamethasone dipropionate fixed-combination therapy is not recommended for areas of thinner skin, such as the face, groin, or axillae, or for any locations where skin atrophy is present.<sup type="ref">[14]</sup> Both skin and psoriatic lesions on the scalp tend to be thick. Higher potency topical corticosteroids and/or calcipotriene have been extensively studied in scalp disease and are standard therapies for this location. Salicylic acid and other desquamating agents can also be helpful for penetrating these lesions.<sup type="ref">[2,8]</sup>
</p>
<p>Choice of vehicle can affect medication penetration, onset of activity, and patient adherence to topical regimens.<sup type="ref">[10]</sup> Studies using human skin samples have shown that skin penetration varies both by vehicle and by body location, with skin from the palms and soles being significantly more difficult to penetrate.<sup type="ref">[21]</sup> In general, ointments are most effective at penetrating thick lesions, but may be less acceptable to patients because of their greasy nature. Creams are somewhat less effective but may be more cosmetically appealing. Lotions and gels are useful for hairy areas because they penetrate easily without leaving a greasy residue. Foams, mousses, and shampoos are also useful for treating hairy areas, particularly the scalp.<sup type="ref">[10]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Adherence, Monitoring, and Follow-Up</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Although topical therapies for psoriasis are generally well-tolerated, patients should receive regular examinations to ensure that they are using their medications correctly, assess treatment effectiveness, and monitor for adherence and adverse effects.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Adherence to topical therapies for psoriasis can be low, ranging from 35% to 71%.<sup type="ref">[22]</sup> Overall, about half of patients with psoriasis fail to fill their prescriptions, and one-third to two-third use their medications incorrectly. Reasons for poor adherence can be patient-related; for example, the stress, anxiety, and other psychosocial deficits associated with having psoriasis may sap patient motivation or make them forget to use their medications. Lack of adherence can also be related to the physician-patient relationship. Inadequate education and poor communication can lead to lack of patient knowledge about the purposes of therapies, lack of trust, and unrealistic expectations for treatment outcomes. Early follow-up has been shown to improve this relationship and patient adherence.<sup type="ref">[23]</sup>
</p>
<p>American Academy of Dermatology guidelines suggest that the optimal choice of topical therapy is the one the patient will actually use, underscoring the importance of considering patient preference for vehicle and other treatment characteristics.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup> Heavy or greasy vehicles or odors may reduce patient adherence, although vehicle preferences can vary considerably from one patient to another.<sup type="ref">[8,23]</sup> Fear of side effects, slow-acting treatments, excessive time to apply therapies, and regimens that involve frequent application can also reduce patient adherence.<sup type="ref">[23]</sup> In addition to consulting patient preferences, patient age, motivation, and ability to adhere to complex treatment regimens should be considered. Fixed-combination regimens can help reduce side effects and simplify treatment regimens.<sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 1 (Cont): Long-Term Follow-up</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Jessica starts treatment with a class II high-potency topical corticosteroid cream that she applies to the plaques on her knees and elbows. She applies a high-potency topical steroid solution to her scalp with use of a salicylic-acid containing shampoo. Jessica responds well for about 1 year, with her psoriasis controlled to less than 1% BSA. However, over the next 2 years her psoriasis gradually worsens until it is at about 5% BSA, despite good adherence on her part and a switch to a higher potency class I corticosteroid. She develops multiple thin plaques that continue to spread on the extensor surfaces and flexures of her arms and legs. After ruling out an underlying infection, you consider next steps. Jessica says that she does not feel ready to begin systemic therapy at this time.</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>8</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Phototherapy</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Phototherapy has long been used to treat psoriasis and remains an important treatment modality. Although many types and sources of light have been tested, NB-UVB and excimer (308 nm) or pulsed dye laser are the primary modalities used in the United States (Table 5).<sup type="ref">[24]</sup> Selection of modality depends on the type and location of psoriasis as well as percent of BSA coverage. Depending on the type and amount of phototherapy used, patients may need frequent, long-term monitoring for skin cancer. Particular care must be taken in patients with a history of photosensitivity or skin cancer, patients at increased risk for skin cancer, and patients who are immunosuppressed.<sup type="ref">[25]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Table 5. Common Types of Phototherapy for Treating Psoriasis<sup type="ref">[24,25]</sup> </strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <table class="inline_data_table">
    <tbody>
        <tr valign="top">
            <th>Type</th>
            <th>Wavelengths</th>
            <th>Indications</th>
            <th>Notes</th>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>NB-UVB</td>
            <td>311 nm</td>
            <td>Stable plaque psoriasis<br/>&gt;10% BSA<br/>Unresponsive to topicals</td>
            <td>May see improvement within 2 weeks<br/>Remission rate 38% at 1 year</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>UVB phototherapy by excimer laser</td>
            <td>308 nm</td>
            <td>Localized plaque psoriasis &lt;10% BSA (eg, palms, soles, elbows, knees)</td>
            <td>Treats only involved area, reducing risk to surrounding skin<br/>Requires fewer sessions<br/>Shorter remissions</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Systemic PUVA</td>
            <td>320 to 400 nm</td>
            <td>Stable plaque psoriasis, palmoplantar psoriasis resistant to topical therapy</td>
            <td>Rarely used in the United States Remission time 3 to 12 months<br/>Oral 8-methoxypsoralen used for sensitization is associated with additional side effects, most commonly nausea and vomiting<br/>Demonstrated risk of skin cancer<br/>UV sensitization persists requiring caution with sun exposure and protective eyewear</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Pulsed dye laser therapy</td>
            <td>585 to 595 nm</td>
            <td>Nail psoriasis, localized plaque psoriasis</td>
            <td>Higher wavelength may penetrate nails more effectively than UVB<br/>Treats only involved area, reducing risk to surrounding skin</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 1: Conclusion</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>You recommend NB-UVB phototherapy, explaining to Jessica that she will need treatment 3 times a week for a total of 20 to 25 sessions. Jessica is a bit concerned about the inconvenience involved, but opts to try it. After 10 treatment sessions over the course of about 4 weeks, she starts to see improvement, and after 20 treatment sessions her psoriasis has returned to less than 1% BSA coverage. If Jessica's psoriasis spreads again, she will need to continue with topical therapies and consider additional phototherapy.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 2: Patient History</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <table align="left" border="1" bordercolor="#b3b3b3" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" style="margin-right: 20px;">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td align="center">
<img alt="" border="0" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/894/123/894123-patient2.jpg?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=200:150" width="200"/>
</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>

<p>Brian is a 40-year-old man with chronic plaque psoriasis for the past 7 years. He was previously treated with methotrexate and topical therapies with limited treatment success. Brian is in your office today in great distress because his psoriasis has worsened considerably over the past few months. He complains about intense itching and pain. Brian also remarked that he has overheard customers remark about his "skin infection" and "contagious condition", which is causing psychological distress.</p>
<p>On physical examination you note:</p>

<ul>
    <li>Multiple large thickened plaques on trunk, buttocks, legs, and arms</li>
    <li>Nail involvement with extensive pitting, some hyperkeratosis, and onycholysis in 7/10 fingernails</li>
    <li>He has about 12 palms worth of psoriasis -- estimated at about 12% BSA involvement</li>
</ul>

<p>Brian is a smoker and drinks alcohol. He is also about 40 pounds overweight and takes medications for hypertension and high cholesterol. His psoriasis is moderate to severe based on BSA and the negative impact on QoL.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Figure 3. Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis</strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>
<img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/894/123/894123-fig3.png"/>
</p>

<blockquote>Photo courtesy of Jeffrey J. Crowley, MD.</blockquote>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>9</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Medical Comorbidities of Psoriasis</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Psoriasis is an inflammatory condition with manifestations that go beyond cutaneous and joint-related symptoms. As in other inflammatory, autoimmune conditions, such as rheumatoid arthritis and systemic lupus erythematosus, psoriasis is associated with high rates of cardiovascular disease, obesity, and metabolic syndrome.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> Baseline analysis of 11,900 patients (mean age 48.6 years) in the PSOLAR longitudinal psoriasis registry found high rates of overweight and obesity (80%), cardiovascular disease (38.2%), hypertension (29.7%), and hyperlipidemia (18.6%). Many patients had a history of pulmonary disease and diabetes as well.<sup type="ref">[4]</sup> Patients with psoriasis are also much more likely than individuals without psoriasis to have an inflammatory bowel disease, such as Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis, perhaps reflecting a shared underlying genetic susceptibility.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> These comorbidities can contribute substantially to the loss of QoL and work impairment experienced by patients with psoriasis.<sup type="ref">[5]</sup>
</p>
<p>Psoriatic arthritis is another common comorbidity that can cause pain and loss of mobility, and reduces QoL and work productivity in patients with psoriasis.<sup type="ref">[26]</sup> In the PSOLAR registry, 35.5% of patients with psoriasis also had psoriatic arthritis.<sup type="ref">[4]</sup> Psoriatic arthritis presents as joint or digit swelling but can involve the axial skeleton as well and present as back pain.<sup type="ref">[2]</sup> This comorbidity typically develops about 10 to 12 years after the onset of psoriasis and is thus less prevalent in younger patients with psoriasis.<sup type="ref">[26]</sup> Patients with nail involvement and those with intergluteal/perianal or scalp psoriasis are 2 to 4 times more likely to develop psoriatic arthritis compared with patients whose psoriasis does not involve these sites.<sup type="ref">[27]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>10</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Systemic Treatment: Biologic Agents</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Biologic agents, which include tumor necrosis factor (TNF), IL-12/IL-23, IL-17, and selective IL-23 inhibitors, are the most efficacious systemic therapies for psoriasis. Anti-TNF agents were the first biologic therapies for psoriasis, based on research that implicated TNF-alpha as a key mediator of inflammation in this condition.<sup>[28]</sup> Anti-TNF agents include adalimumab, etanercept, and infliximab. Table 6 shows the efficacies of these agents in comparison with the newer biologics. Anti-TNF agents are used in a wide range of autoimmune disorders, with clinical experience that includes millions of patients.<a href="javascript:pop_layer('references_layer');">
<sup>[1]</sup>
</a>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Table 6. FDA Approved Biologics for Psoriasis<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> </strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <table class="inline_data_table">
    <tbody>
        <tr valign="top">
            <th>Class</th>
            <th>Agent</th>
            <th>PASI 75 (%)</th>
            <th>Results at Week</th>
            <th>Dosing</th>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="3">Anti-TNF</td>
            <td>Adalimumab<sup type="ref">[29]</sup>
</td>
            <td>71</td>
            <td>16</td>
            <td>80 mg SC initial dose; 40 mg every other week</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Etanercept<sup type="ref">[30]</sup>
</td>
            <td>46</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>50 mg SC twice a week</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Infliximab<sup type="ref">[31]</sup>
</td>
            <td>80</td>
            <td>10</td>
            <td>5 mg/kg IV weeks 0, 2, and 6</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>IL-12/IL-23</td>
            <td>Ustekinuma<sup type="ref">[32]</sup>
</td>
            <td>67</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>45 mg SC weeks 0 and 4</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="3">IL-17</td>
            <td>Brodalumab<sup type="ref">[32]</sup>
</td>
            <td>86</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>210 mg SC weeks 0, 1, 2 and every 2 weeks thereafter</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Ixekizumab<sup type="ref">[32]</sup>
</td>
            <td>90</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>160 mg SC initial dose; 80 mg every 2 weeks</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Secukinumab<sup type="ref">[32]</sup>
</td>
            <td>82</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>300 mg SC weeks 1 to 4 and every 4 weeks thereafter</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td rowspan="2">IL-23</td>
            <td>Guselkumab<sup type="ref">[33]</sup>
</td>
            <td>91</td>
            <td>16</td>
            <td>100 mg weeks 0, 4, and 12</td>
        </tr>
        <tr valign="top">
            <td>Tildrakizumab<sup type="ref">[34]</sup>
</td>
            <td>64</td>
            <td>12</td>
            <td>100 mg weeks 0 and 4</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>

<blockquote>IV = intravenous; SC = subcutaneous.</blockquote>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Anti-TNF agents can be associated with reactivation of tuberculosis and hepatitis B.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> Live vaccines should be avoided in patients taking these agents. Anti-TNF agents in particular should not be used in patients with or at high risk of demyelinating diseases, such as multiple sclerosis, and should be avoided in patients with congestive heart failure, particularly those with ejection fraction lower than 50%.<sup type="ref">[1]</sup> Anti-TNF agents are also associated with rare hematologic disorders and malignancies, including cases of lymphoma.<sup type="ref">[29-31]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Adalimumab.</strong> Adalimumab is FDA approved for moderate to severe plaque psoriasis in adult patients who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy, and when other systemic therapies are medically less appropriate. Common AEs include infections (eg, upper respiratory, sinusitis), injection site reactions, headache, and rash.<sup type="ref">[29]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Etanercept.</strong> Etanercept is FDA approved for treatment of plaque psoriasis in patients aged 4 years and older. Common AEs include infections and injection site reactions.<sup type="ref">[30]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Infliximab.</strong> Infliximab is FDA approved for chronic severe plaque psoriasis in adult patients who are candidates for systemic therapy when other systemic treatment options are not deemed medically appropriate. Infliximab is contraindicated in patients with previous severe hypersensitivity reactions, and higher doses are contraindicated in patients with moderate to severe heart failure. Common AEs include infections (eg, upper respiratory, sinusitis, and pharyngitis), infusion-related reactions, headache, and abdominal pain.<sup type="ref">[31]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Interleukin-Targeted Agents</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>The IL-17/IL-23 inflammatory pathways are thought to play key roles in the immunopathophysiology of psoriasis.</p>
<p>
<strong>Ustekinumab. </strong>Ustekinumab, a monoclonal antibody that targets IL-12 and IL-23 subunit p40, was one of the first successful agents to target this pathway.<sup type="ref">[32]</sup> Ustekinumab was FDA approved in 2009 for patients aged 12 years or older with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[35]</sup> Phase 3 RCTs have shown that ustekinumab is more efficacious for treating psoriasis than placebo or etanercept.<sup type="ref">[32]</sup> The most common AEs in patients with psoriasis are nasopharyngitis, upper respiratory tract infection, headache, and fatigue. The prescribing information for ustekinumab includes warnings and precautions for very rare AEs, such hypersensitivity reactions, serious infections, and malignancies.<sup type="ref">[35]</sup>
</p>
<p>Since the development of ustekinumab, the role of IL-12 has been questioned in psoriasis, leading to development of agents that target IL-17- and IL-23-mediated events. Five new agents have been approved in the last few years.<sup type="ref">[32]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Brodalumab. </strong>Brodalumab is a monoclonal antibody that blocks the IL-17 receptor thereby inhibiting the activities of IL-17A, IL-17F, IL-17A/F, IL-17C, and IL-25.<sup type="ref">[32]</sup> Brodalumab is FDA approved for treating moderate to severe plaque psoriasis in adult patients who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy and have failed to respond or lost response to other systemic therapies.<sup type="ref">[36]</sup> The AMAGINE-1 trial compared brodalumab 210-mg or 140-mg doses (administered every 2 weeks) with placebo while the AMAGINE-2 and AMAGINE-3 trials included an additional arm for comparison with ustekinumab. At week 12, the brodalumab 210-mg dose was associated with PASI75 response rates of 83% to 86%, compared with 3% to 8% for placebo. PASI score reduced by 100% (PASI100) rates at 12 weeks were 37% to 44% for brodalumab 210 mg compared with 19% to 22% for ustekinumab (<em>P </em>&lt;.001 for all comparisons).<sup type="ref">[37,38]</sup>
</p>
<p>The most common AEs associated with brodalumab in clinical trials were arthralgia, headache, and fatigue.<sup type="ref">[37,38]</sup> Brodalumab is contraindicated in patients with Crohn's disease and carries a boxed warning for association with suicidal ideation and behavior, necessitating participation in a risk evaluation and mitigation strategy program.<sup type="ref">[36]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Ixekizumab. </strong>Ixekizumab is a humanized IL-17A monoclonal antibody that is FDA approved for adult patients with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[39]</sup> The UNCOVER-2 and UNCOVER-3 trials found that ixekizumab was associated with a PASI75 rate of 87.3% at 12 weeks in patients who received the 80-mg dose every 2 weeks (after an initial loading dose of 160 mg), compared with 7.3% for placebo. PASI100 was 37.7% at 12 weeks compared with 7.3% for etanercept (<em>P </em>&lt;.0001 for all comparisons).<sup type="ref">[40]</sup> Extension of UNCOVER-3 to 108 weeks found continued efficacy with long-term administration of 80 mg every 4 weeks.<sup type="ref">[41]</sup>
</p>
<p>The most common AEs associated with ixekizumab are injection site reactions, upper respiratory infections, nausea, and tinea infections. Hypersensitivity reactions, serious infections, and exacerbations of Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis are also associated with ixekizumab treatment.<sup type="ref">[39]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Secukinumab.</strong> Secukinumab is a human IL-17A targeted monoclonal antibody that is FDA approved for adult patients with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[42]</sup> The ERASURE and FIXTURE trials compared 300-mg or 150-mg secukinumab administered once weekly for 5 weeks, then every 4 weeks until week 48. PASI75 rates for the 300-mg dose were 77.1% to 81.6% at 12 weeks compared with 4.5% to 4.9% for placebo. In the FIXTURE trial, PASI100 was 24.1% at 12 weeks compared with 4.3% for etanercept (<em>P </em>&lt;.001 for all comparisons).<sup type="ref">[43]</sup> The CLEAR trial, which compared secukinumab to ustekinumab, found a PASI score reduced by 90% (PASI90) rate at 16 weeks of 79.0% for secukinumab 300 mg compared with 57.5% for ustekinumab dosed per label (<em>P </em>&lt;.0001).<sup type="ref">[44]</sup>
</p>
<p>The most common AEs associated with secukinumab are nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, and upper respiratory infection. Rare AEs include hypersensitivity reactions, serious infections, and inflammatory bowel disease.<sup type="ref">[42]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Guselkumab. </strong>Guselkumab is an IL-23 targeted monoclonal antibody that is approved for adult patients with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[45]</sup> The VOYAGE-1 and VOYAGE-2 trials compared guselkumab 100 mg (administered at baseline, week 4, and week 12, then every 8 weeks to week 44) with placebo and adalimumab. At 16 weeks, the PASI75 rate was 86.3% to 91.2% for guselkumab compared with 68.5% to 73.1% for adalimumab and 5.7% to 8.1% for placebo. PASI100 was 34.1% to 37.4% for guselkumab compared with 17.1% to 20.6% for adalimumab. Significantly improved responses with guselkumab were maintained at weeks 24 and 48 compared with adalimumab (<em>P </em>&lt;.001 for all comparisons).<sup type="ref">[33,46]</sup>
</p>
<p>The most common AEs associated with guselkumab are upper respiratory infections, headache, injection site reactions, arthralgia, diarrhea, gastroenteritis, tinea infections, and herpes simplex infections.<sup type="ref">[45]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Tildrakizumab. </strong>Tildrakizumab is a humanized monoclonal antibody targeted to IL-23 that was FDA approved in March 2018 for adults with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[47]</sup>
</p>
<p>Tildrakizumab was evaluated in the multi-part reSURFACE trials. In reSURFACE-1 part 1, patients were randomized to receive tildrakizumab at 200-mg or 100-mg doses or placebo (administered at baseline, week 4, and subsequently every 12 weeks) with primary endpoint evaluation at week 12. In reSURFACE-2 part 1, patients were randomized to tildrakizumab 200 mg or 100 mg, placebo, or etanercept. At 12 weeks, PASI75 rates were 62% to 66% for tildrakizumab 200 mg compared with 6% for placebo. Response rates continued to improve through week 28. PASI100 rates were 12% for tildrakizumab compared with 5% for etanercept at 12 weeks (<em>P </em>&lt;.0001 for all comparisons). The most common AEs associated with tildrakizumab were nasopharyngitis and upper respiratory tract infection.<sup type="ref">[34]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Systemic Treatment: Non-Biologic Therapies</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Multiple non-biologic systemic therapies can be used to treat psoriasis, including acitretin, apremilast, cyclosporine, and methotrexate. In general there is less evidence for the efficacy of these therapies compared with biologics, but they are useful in certain situations, particularly where oral administration is desired.<sup type="ref">[1,48]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Acitretin.</strong> Acitretin is FDA approved for adult patients with severe plaque psoriasis. Acitretin requires 3 to 6 months of dosing to achieve a maximal response with optimal safety and tolerability. Careful patient selection and monitoring are needed to prevent or manage a long list of potential toxicities, which include mucocutaneous side effects, metabolic effects such as dyslipidemia, and organ toxicities. Acitretin is a teratogenic agent that should not be used in women of childbearing potential.<sup type="ref">[48]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Apremilast.</strong> Apremilast is a newer oral, non-biologic therapy that was first approved in 2014. Apremilast is a phosphodiesterase 4 inhibitor that is indicated for patients with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are candidates for systemic therapy or phototherapy.<sup type="ref">[49]</sup> The phase 3 ESTEEM-1 trial showed a PASI75 of 33.1% at week 16 in patients with chronic plaque psoriasis.<sup type="ref">[50]</sup> Apremilast has fewer toxicities than older oral systemic agents for psoriasis but can cause severe gastrointestinal distress and is associated with increased risk for depression. The most common adverse reactions are diarrhea, nausea, upper respiratory tract infection, and headache. Hypersensitivity reactions, weight loss, and drug interactions may also occur. Patients with severe renal impairment require dose reductions. Apremilast should only be used in pregnancy if potential benefits outweigh potential risks to the fetus.<sup type="ref">[49]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Cyclosporine.<em> </em> </strong>Cyclosporine is an immunosuppressive agent that is indicated for non-immunocompromised, adult patients with extensive or disabling, recalcitrant plaque psoriasis. Cyclosporine is an effective short-term treatment but is not recommended for long-term treatment because of potential toxicities, the most serious of which are nephrotoxicity and hypertension. Cyclosporine is associated with many potential medication interactions. Patients should be carefully selected, evaluated, and monitored. This agent should only be used in pregnancy if the potential benefits outweigh potential risks.<sup type="ref">[48]</sup>
</p>
<p>
<strong>Methotrexate.</strong> Methotrexate is a dihydrofolate reductase inhibitor that is indicated for patients with severe, recalcitrant, disabling psoriasis that does not respond adequately to other forms of treatment. A placebo-controlled trial of methotrexate found a PASI75 of 36% after 16 weeks for patients treated with 7.5 mg/week orally, increased as needed up to 25 mg/week. However, methotrexate can be highly effective in some patients. Methotrexate is associated with a number of potentially serious toxicities, including myelosuppression, hepatotoxicity, and pulmonary fibrosis, that necessitate careful patient selection and monitoring. More common, less severe toxicities include nausea, anorexia, stomatitis, and fatigue. Methotrexate is a teratogen and is contraindicated in both men and women of childbearing potential.<sup type="ref">[48]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Considerations for Systemic Treatment Selection</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>Selection of systemic therapies for patients with psoriasis depends on treatment characteristics, including efficacy, safety profile, and potential for interaction with other medications, and patient characteristics such as disease severity and location, effects on psychological health and QoL, age, gender, and comorbidities.<sup type="ref">[1,48,49]</sup> Patient preferences for route of administration and tolerability of side effects should also be considered.<sup type="ref">[23]</sup> Patients should be screened for infections such as hepatitis B, hepatitis C, tuberculosis, and HIV, as well as for autoimmune conditions such as multiple sclerosis or inflammatory bowel disease. Patients with pre-existing psoriatic arthritis or inflammatory bowel disease may benefit from therapies that also have activity against those conditions. Previous history with psoriasis medications including efficacy, adverse effects, and adherence are also important considerations.<sup type="ref">[1,48,51]</sup>
</p>
<p>Physical comorbidities play an especially important role given the high number of comorbid conditions present in many patients with psoriasis. Overweight and obesity are associated with poor responses to some systemic therapies, including both biologic and non-biologic therapies. Obese patients and those who drink alcohol are at increased risk for fatty liver disease, which is a relative contraindication to some systemic therapies. Some older oral therapies for psoriasis are associated with increased risk for hypertension and dyslipidemia, which should be considered in patients who already have or are at risk for these conditions. Metabolic conditions such as diabetes and obesity, which put patients at higher risk for kidney disease, should also be taken into account when considering therapies with potential nephrotoxicity.<sup type="ref">[51]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 2 (Cont): Treatment Selection</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>After discussing treatment options with Brian, you decide on a course of adalimumab plus topical treatment with high-potency corticosteroids. Brian's psoriasis improves to 1% to 2% BSA involvement over the next 3 months. At 6 months, however, Brian returns with worsening psoriasis that has spread to 4% BSA over the past month. Brian has been adherent to his medications. He is very uncomfortable and desires quick relief from his rapidly spreading psoriasis.</p>
        </slide_intro>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>11</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Comparing Time to Onset Among Biologic Therapies</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>In addition to efficacy, patients with psoriasis place a high value on rapid disease control, particularly in moderate to severe cases. A recent systematic review analyzed the time to onset of action of 7 biologic therapies based on available clinical data. Time to onset of action is not usually included as a primary or secondary endpoint in clinical trials; however, the investigators were able to estimate time to onset of action based on linear interpolation of published time courses of patient improvement. Based on time until 25% of patients achieved a PASI75 response, they found that the IL-17 targeted biologics had the fastest time to response, ranging from 2.1 weeks for brodalumab to 3.0 weeks for secukinumab (Figure 4). Overall, time to onset for these 7 biologics ranged from 2 to 11 weeks.<sup type="ref">[52]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>
<strong>Figure 4. Times to Onset of Biologic Therapies for Psoriasis<sup>[52]</sup>
</strong>
</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>
<img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/894/123/894123-fig4.png"/>
</p>

<blockquote>CI = confidence interval.<br/>Papp KA, Lebwohl MG. Onset of action of biologics in patients with moderate-to-severe psoriasis. <em>J Drugs Dermatol</em>. 2018;17:247-250.</blockquote>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Treat to Target Guidelines for Psoriasis</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>The advent of increasingly effective therapies for psoriasis has led to calls for more stringent treatment targets for these patients, equivalent to the clinical trial endpoints of PASI90 or PASI100. Reaching complete remission is associated with improved QoL in patients with psoriasis, whereas patients with an incomplete response to treatment often have a high remaining symptom burden and reduced QoL.<sup type="ref">[28]</sup>
</p>
<p>In 2016, the National Psoriasis Foundation released a new consensus guideline that outlined acceptable and preferred treatment targets for patients with psoriasis. Although BSA involvement of 3% or less or BSA improvement of 75% or more from baseline were considered acceptable outcomes at 3 months after treatment initiation, these new guidelines preferred targets of BSA involvement of 1% or less at 3 months after treatment initiation, and BSA involvement of 1% or less at every 6-month assessment interval during maintenance treatment. The guideline writers emphasized that these preferred targets are goals that patients and clinicians should strive for, but that may not be possible or necessary for all patients.<sup type="ref">[53]</sup>
</p>
<p>These new treatment targets represent a yardstick against which clinicians can monitor treatment progression and patient response to treatment. Failure to meet these goals should be considered a reason to re-evaluate the existing treatment regimen and consider escalating treatment, adding another agent for combination therapy, or switching to another therapy altogether. Although BSA was selected as the most practical measure for use by general dermatologists, the guideline writers recognized that BSA does not capture many disease aspects that are important to patients, including disease location, symptoms, comorbidities, and QoL impacts. Overall, treatment decisions should continue to be made on an individualized basis and include ongoing discussions between patients and clinicians that take into account patients' preferences, needs, and life circumstances.<sup type="ref">[53]</sup>
</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Case 2: Conclusion</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>After discussion with Brian, he is started on a course of brodalumab with continued use of high-potency topical corticosteroids. Brian's psoriasis begins to remit after about 3 weeks of treatment. At 3 months he is greatly improved, with about a 1% BSA involvement. He will return after another 3 months for further evaluation of his treatment progress.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header>
          <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
        </subsec_header>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>What did you learn from this activity? Please click on the "Next" button to proceed to a brief survey to see how your knowledge improved after the education. You can also see how your answers compare with those of your peers.</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro/>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form>13</qna_form>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro/>
        <slide_grp>
          <sec_img/>
          <sec_label/>
          <sec_caption/>
          <sec_txt/>
          <sec_alt_txt/>
          <qna_form/>
        </slide_grp>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label>
      <p>Abbreviations</p>
    </toc_label>
    <toc_type>Sidebar</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header>
        <p>Abbreviations</p>
      </sec_header>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <p>AAD = American Academy of Dermatology<br/>
AEs = adverse events<br/>
BSA = body surface area<br/>
CI = confidence interval<br/>
DLQI = Dermatology Life Quality Index<br/>
FDA = US Food and Drug Administration<br/>
HPA = hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis<br/>
IGA = Investigators Global Assessment <br/>
IL = interleukin<br/>
ISI = Itch Severity Item <br/>
IV = intravenous<br/>
MAPP = Multinational Assessment of Psoriasis and Psoriatic Arthritis <br/>
NB-UVB = narrow band UVB phototherapy <br/>
PUVA = psoralen ultraviolet A phototherapy<br/>
OTC = over the counter<br/>
PASI = Psoriasis Area and Severity Index<br/>
PASI75 = PASI score reduced by 75% <br/>
PASI90 = PASI score reduced by 90% <br/>
PASI100 = PASI score reduced by 100% <br/>
PGA = Physicians Global Assessment <br/>
QoL = quality of life<br/>
RCTs = randomized controlled trials<br/>
SC = subcutaneous<br/>
TNF = tumor necrosis factor <br/>
TrkA = tropomyosin receptor kinase A<br/>
UVB = ultraviolet B<br/>
VAS = visual analogue scale</p>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <toc_element>
    <toc_label/>
    <toc_type>References</toc_type>
    <pg_footnotes/>
    <sec_element>
      <sec_header/>
      <subsec_element>
        <subsec_header/>
        <slide_intro>
          <ol>
    <li>Menter A, Gottlieb A, Feldman SR, et al. Guidelines of care for the management of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: Section 1. Overview of psoriasis and guidelines of care for the treatment of psoriasis with biologics. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2008;58:826-850.</li>
    <li>Kim WB, Jerome D, Yeung J. Diagnosis and management of psoriasis. <em>Can Fam Physician. </em>2017;63:278-285.</li>
    <li>Clarke P. Psoriasis. <em>Aust Fam Physician. </em>2011;40:468-473.</li>
    <li>Kimball AB, Leonardi C, Stahle M, et al. Demography, baseline disease characteristics and treatment history of patients with psoriasis enrolled in a multicentre, prospective, disease-based registry (PSOLAR). <em>Br J Dermatol. </em>2014;171:137-147.</li>
    <li>Griffiths CEM, Jo SJ, Naldi L, et al. A multidimensional assessment of the burden of psoriasis: results from a multinational dermatologist and patient survey. <em>Br J Dermatol. </em>2018. doi:10.1111/bjd.16332. [Epub ahead of print]</li>
    <li>Lebwohl MG, Kavanaugh A, Armstrong AW, Van Voorhees AS. US perspectives in the management of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: patient and physician results from the population-based Multinational Assessment of Psoriasis and Psoriatic Arthritis (MAPP) survey. <em>Am J Clin Dermatol. </em>2016;17:87-97.</li>
    <li>Strober B, Gooderham M, de Jong E, et al. Depressive symptoms, depression, and the effect of biologic therapy among patients in Psoriasis Longitudinal Assessment and Registry (PSOLAR). <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2018;78:70-80.</li>
    <li>Menter A, Korman NJ, Elmets CA, et al. Guidelines of care for the management of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis. Section 3. Guidelines of care for the management and treatment of psoriasis with topical therapies. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2009;60:643-659.</li>
    <li>Sarbacker GB, Witte AP, Maize DF. Overview of plaque psoriasis treatment. <em>US Pharmacist</em>. https://www.uspharmacist.com/ce/overview-of-plaque-psoriasis-treatment. Published June 1, 2016. Accessed March 29, 2018.</li>
    <li>Ference JD, Last AR. Choosing topical corticosteroids. <em>Am Fam Physician. </em>2009;79:135-140.</li>
    <li>Mason A, Mason J, Cork M, et al. Topical treatments for chronic plaque psoriasis: an abridged Cochrane systematic review. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2013;69:799-807.</li>
    <li>Ashcroft DM, Po AL, Williams HC, Griffiths CE. Systematic review of comparative efficacy and tolerability of calcipotriol in treating chronic plaque psoriasis. <em>BMJ. </em>2000;320:963-967.</li>
    <li>Patel NU, Felix K, Reimer D, Feldman SR. Calcipotriene/betamethasone dipropionate for the treatment of psoriasis vulgaris: an evidence-based review. <em>Clin Cosmet Investig Dermatol. </em>2017;10:385-391.</li>
    <li>Taclonex® [prescribing information]. Madison, NJ: LEO Pharma Inc.; 2017.</li>
    <li>Leonardi C, Bagel J, Yamauchi P, et al. Efficacy and safety of calcipotriene plus betamethasone dipropionate aerosol foam in patients with psoriasis vulgaris -- a randomized phase III study (PSO-FAST). <em>J Drugs Dermatol. </em>2015;14:1468-1477.</li>
    <li>Enstilar® [prescribing information]. Madison, NJ: LEO Pharma Inc.; 2017.</li>
    <li>Chi CC, Mayon-White RT, Wojnarowska FT. Safety of topical corticosteroids in pregnancy: a population-based cohort study. <em>J Invest Dermatol. </em>2011;131:884-891.</li>
    <li>Gold LS, Lebwohl MG, Sugarman JL, et al. Safety and efficacy of a halobetasol/tazarotene fixed combination in the treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis: results of two phase 3 randomized controlled trials. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol</em>. 2018. doi:10.1016/j.jaad.2018.03.040. [Epub ahead of print]</li>
    <li>Papp KA, Bissonnette R, Gooderham M, et al. Treatment of plaque psoriasis with an ointment formulation of the Janus kinase inhibitor, tofacitinib: a phase 2b randomized clinical trial. <em>BMC Dermatol. </em>2016;16:15.</li>
    <li>Roblin D, Yosipovitch G, Boyce B, et al. Topical TrkA kinase inhibitor CT327 is an effective, novel therapy for the treatment of pruritus due to psoriasis: results from experimental studies, and efficacy and safety of CT327 in a phase 2b clinical trial in patients with psoriasis. <em>Acta Derm Venereol. </em>2015;95:542-548.</li>
    <li>Huang X, Tanojo H, Lenn J, et al. A novel foam vehicle for delivery of topical corticosteroids. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2005;53(1 suppl 1):S26-S38.</li>
    <li>Belinchon I, Rivera R, Blanch C, et al. Adherence, satisfaction and preferences for treatment in patients with psoriasis in the European Union: a systematic review of the literature. <em>Patient Prefer Adherence. </em>2016;10:2357-2367.</li>
    <li>Yelamos O, Ros S, Puig L. Improving patient outcomes in psoriasis: strategies to ensure treatment adherence. <em>Psoriasis (Auckl). </em>2015;5:109-115.</li>
    <li>Zhang P, Wu MX. A clinical review of phototherapy for psoriasis. <em>Lasers Med Sci. </em>2018;33:173-180.</li>
    <li>Menter A, Korman NJ, Elmets CA, et al. Guidelines of care for the management of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: Section 5. Guidelines of care for the treatment of psoriasis with phototherapy and photochemotherapy. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2010;62:114-135.</li>
    <li>Gottlieb A, Korman NJ, Gordon KB, et al. Guidelines of care for the management of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: Section 2. Psoriatic arthritis: overview and guidelines of care for treatment with an emphasis on the biologics. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2008;58:851-864.</li>
    <li>Wilson FC, Icen M, Crowson CS, et al. Incidence and clinical predictors of psoriatic arthritis in patients with psoriasis: a population-based study. <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2009;61:233-239.</li>
    <li>Wu JJ. Contemporary management of moderate to severe plaque psoriasis. <em>Am J Manag Care. </em>2017;23(21 suppl):S403-S416.</li>
    <li>Humira® [prescribing information]. North Chicago, IL: AbbVie Inc.; 2017.</li>
    <li>Enbrel® [prescribing information]. Thousand Oaks, CA: Amgen Inc. (Immunex Corporation); 2017.</li>
    <li>Remicade® [prescribing information]. Horsham, PA: Janssen Biotech, Inc.; 2017.</li>
    <li>Tsai YC, Tsai TF. Anti-interleukin and interleukin therapies for psoriasis: current evidence and clinical usefulness. <em>Ther Adv Musculoskelet Dis. </em>2017;9:277-294.</li>
    <li>Blauvelt A, Papp KA, Griffiths CE, et al. Efficacy and safety of guselkumab, an anti-interleukin-23 monoclonal antibody, compared with adalimumab for the continuous treatment of patients with moderate to severe psoriasis: results from the phase III, double-blinded, placebo- and active comparator-controlled VOYAGE 1 trial. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2017;76:405-417.</li>
    <li>Reich K, Papp KA, Blauvelt A, et al. Tildrakizumab versus placebo or etanercept for chronic plaque psoriasis (reSURFACE 1 and reSURFACE 2): results from two randomised controlled, phase 3 trials. <em>Lancet. </em>2017;390:276-288.</li>
    <li>Stelara® [prescribing information]. Horsham, PA: Janssen Biotech, Inc.; 2018.</li>
    <li>Siliq™ [prescribing information]. Bridgewater, NJ: Valeant Pharmaceuticals; 2017.</li>
    <li>Papp KA, Reich K, Paul C, et al. A prospective phase III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study of brodalumab in patients with moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis. <em>Br J Dermatol. </em>2016;175:273-286.</li>
    <li>Lebwohl M, Strober B, Menter A, et al. Phase 3 studies comparing brodalumab with ustekinumab in psoriasis. <em>N Engl J Med. </em>2015;373:1318-1328.</li>
    <li>Taltz® [prescribing information]. Indianapolis, IN: Eli Lilly and Company; 2017.</li>
    <li>Griffiths CE, Reich K, Lebwohl M, et al. Comparison of ixekizumab with etanercept or placebo in moderate-to-severe psoriasis (UNCOVER-2 and UNCOVER-3): results from two phase 3 randomised trials. <em>Lancet. </em>2015;386:541-551.</li>
    <li>Blauvelt A, Gooderham M, Iversen L, et al. Efficacy and safety of ixekizumab for the treatment of moderate-to-severe plaque psoriasis: results through 108 weeks of a randomized, controlled phase 3 clinical trial (UNCOVER-3). <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2017;77:855-862.</li>
    <li>Cosentyx® [prescribing information]. East Hanover, NJ: Novartis Pharmaceuticals Corporation; 2018.</li>
    <li>Langley RG, Elewski BE, Lebwohl M, et al. Secukinumab in plaque psoriasis -- results of two phase 3 trials. <em>N Engl J Med. </em>2014;371:326-338.</li>
    <li>Thaci D, Blauvelt A, Reich K, et al. Secukinumab is superior to ustekinumab in clearing skin of subjects with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis: CLEAR, a randomized controlled trial. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2015;73:400-409.</li>
    <li>Tremfya® [prescribing information]. Horsham, PA: Janssen Biotech; 2017.</li>
    <li>Reich K, Armstrong AW, Foley P, et al. Efficacy and safety of guselkumab, an anti-interleukin-23 monoclonal antibody, compared with adalimumab for the treatment of patients with moderate to severe psoriasis with randomized withdrawal and retreatment: results from the phase III, double-blind, placebo- and active comparator-controlled VOYAGE 2 trial. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2017;76:418-431.</li>
    <li>Novel drug approvals for 2018. US Food and Drug Administration website. https://www.fda.gov/drugs/developmentapprovalprocess/druginnovation/ucm592464.htm. Accessed April 18, 2018.</li>
    <li>Menter A, Korman NJ, Elmets CA, et al. Guidelines of care for the management of psoriasis and psoriatic arthritis: Section 4. Guidelines of care for the management and treatment of psoriasis with traditional systemic agents. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2009;61:451-485.</li>
    <li>Otezla® [prescribing information]. Summit, NJ: Celgene Corporation; 2017.</li>
    <li>Papp K, Reich K, Leonardi CL, et al. Apremilast, an oral phosphodiesterase 4 (PDE4) inhibitor, in patients with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis: results of a phase III, randomized, controlled trial (Efficacy and Safety Trial Evaluating the Effects of Apremilast in Psoriasis [ESTEEM] 1). <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2015;73:37-49.</li>
    <li>Takeshita J, Grewal S, Langan SM, et al. Psoriasis and comorbid diseases: implications for management. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2017;76:393-403.</li>
    <li>Papp KA, Lebwohl MG. Onset of action of biologics in patients with moderate-to-severe psoriasis. <em>J Drugs Dermatol. </em>2018;17:247-250.</li>
    <li>Armstrong AW, Siegel MP, Bagel J, et al. From the Medical Board of the National Psoriasis Foundation: treatment targets for plaque psoriasis. <em>J Am Acad Dermatol. </em>2017;76:290-298.</li>
</ol>
        </slide_intro>
      </subsec_element>
    </sec_element>
  </toc_element>
  <back_label>Back Matter</back_label>
  <ref_grp>
    <ref_item/>
  </ref_grp>
  <cpyrt_holder>
    <p>Medscape, LLC</p>
  </cpyrt_holder>
  <cpyrt_ovrd/>
  <disclmr_ovrd/>
  <bkmtr_front>
    <p>
<strong>Disclaimer</strong>
</p>
<p>The educational activity presented above may involve simulated case-based scenarios. The patients depicted in these scenarios are fictitious and no association with any actual patient is intended or should be inferred.</p>
<p>The material presented here does not necessarily reflect the views of Medscape, LLC, or companies that support educational programming on medscape.org. These materials may discuss therapeutic products that have not been approved by the US Food and Drug Administration and off-label uses of approved products. A qualified healthcare professional should be consulted before using any therapeutic product discussed. Readers should verify all information and data before treating patients or employing any therapies described in this educational activity.</p>
  </bkmtr_front>
  <bkmtr_glossary/>
  <bkmtr_ack/>
  <bkmtr_discl/>
  <bkmtr_funding/>
  <bkmtr_reprnt_addr/>
  <bkmtr_abbr_notes/>
  <bkmtr_last/>
  <img_ttl_bkgrd>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/title_background/banner-psoriasis-2018.jpg</img_ttl_bkgrd>
  <img_publ_logo/>
</prof_article_slide_presentation>
