<prof_article>
    <front_label>Front Matter</front_label>
    <above_title>
        <p>
            <a href="/sites/advances/sle">Clinical Advances in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus: A Focus on Patient-Centered Symptom Management</a>
        </p>
    </above_title>
    <title>
        <p>How Would You Manage These Patients With SLE? Cases and Perspectives</p>
    </title>
    <contrbtr_pre_content>
        <p>As an organization accredited by the ACCME, Medscape, LLC, requires everyone who is in a position to control the content of an education activity to disclose all relevant financial relationships with any commercial interest.  The ACCME defines "relevant financial relationships" as financial relationships in any amount, occurring within the past 12 months, including financial relationships of a spouse or life partner, that could create a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>Medscape, LLC, encourages Authors to identify investigational products or off-label uses of products regulated by the US Food and Drug Administration, at first mention and where appropriate in the content.</p>
    </contrbtr_pre_content>
    <contrbtr_byline>
        <p>Anca D. Askanase, MD, MPH</p>
    </contrbtr_byline>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Faculty</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element chronicleid="0901c79180e0e9f0">
            <contrbtr_nm>Anca D. Askanase, MD, MPH</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Associate Professor of Medicine
                    <br/>Director, Lupus Center
                    <br/>Irving Medical Center
                    <br/>Columbia University
                    <br/>New York, New York
                </p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Anca D. Askanase, MD, MPH, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Askanase does intend to discuss off-label uses of drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                    <br/>
                    <br/>Dr Askanase does not intend to discuss investigational drugs, mechanical devices, biologics, or diagnostics not approved by the FDA for use in the United States.
                </p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_group>
        <contrbtr_type_lbl>Editor</contrbtr_type_lbl>
        <contrbtr_element>
            <contrbtr_nm>Karen Badal, MD, MPH</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Scientific Director, Medscape, LLC</p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Karen Badal, MD, MPH, has disclosed has disclosed the following relevant financial relationships: Owns stock, stock options, or bonds from: Kallyope, Inc.</p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
        <contrbtr_element>
            <contrbtr_nm>Alexandra Howson MA, CHCP, PhD</contrbtr_nm>
            <contrbtr_title>
                <p>Thistle Editorial, LLC</p>
            </contrbtr_title>
            <contrbtr_bio/>
            <contrbtr_disclsr>
                <p>Disclosure: Alexandra Howson MA, CHCP, PhD, has disclosed no relevant financial relationships.</p>
            </contrbtr_disclsr>
        </contrbtr_element>
    </contrbtr_group>
    <contrbtr_bulk_info/>
    <contrbtr_post_content/>
    <supprtr_grant_group>
        <supprtr_grant_attr>/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/grant_attribution/glaxosmithkline-ieg-txt-2014.gif</supprtr_grant_attr>
    </supprtr_grant_group>
    <body_label>Body</body_label>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The following cases are modeled on the interactive grand rounds approach. The questions within the activity are designed to test your current knowledge. After each question, you will be able to see whether you answered correctly and read evidence-based information that supports the most appropriate answer choice. The questions are designed to challenge you; you will not be penalized for answering the questions incorrectly. At the end of the activity, there will be a short post-test assessment based on the material presented.</p>
                    <div class="downloadbtn">
                        <div class="downloadbtn_lt"></div>
                        <div class="downloadbtn_bg_pdf">
                            <a href="/px/trk.svr/902371?exturl=http://img.medscape.com/images/902/371/ForYourPatient.pdf" target="_blank">For Your Patient</a>
                        </div>
                        <div class="downloadbtn_rt"></div>
                        <div class="spacer"></div>
                    </div>
                    <div class="spacer"></div>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1: Patient History</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table align="left" border="1" bordercolor="#b3b3b3" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" style="margin-right: 20px;">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="center">
                                    <img alt="" border="0" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/371/902371-patient1.png?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=200:150"/>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p style="min-height: 230px;">Jeanette is a 41-year-old woman with a 5-year history of mild mucocutaneous and musculoskeletal lupus. Her symptoms are reasonably controlled with daily hydroxychloroquine (HCQ) 300 mg, but lately she is concerned about “feeling tired all the time” and has some wrist pain. Jeanette is currently under a lot of stress from her work as a Certified Public Accountant. She has been trying to manage this stress through increased physical activity, which involves a new kettlebell workout. She feels that regular exercise helps her manage her fatigue but thinks overexertion might be causing the wrist pain.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>3</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a complex, multisystem autoimmune disease associated with a wide range of clinical manifestations that affects over 300,000 adults in the United States.
                        <sup type="ref">[2]</sup> As a result of the disease heterogeneity, the prevalence and incidence of SLE have been challenging to estimate. Recent epidemiologic research using the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) classification criteria for SLE and evaluating a wide range of data sources, including lupus registries, indicates that globally, North America has the highest estimates for incidence and prevalence (approximately 5.5/100,000 and 75/100,000 person years, respectively).
                        <sup type="ref">[3-7]</sup> These data also show that in the United States, both incidence and prevalence of SLE are higher in women compared with men across every ethnic group and age. Incidence and prevalence of SLE in the United States are highest in African Americans. Asian and Hispanic populations have higher incidence and prevalence compared with Caucasians but lower than African Americans. The overall average age at diagnosis is 39 years, and 34 years for African American patients with SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[7] </sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although the causes of SLE are not fully defined, symptoms are likely driven by the production of pathogenic autoantibodies and dysregulated immune responses.
                        <sup type="ref">[8]</sup> SLE symptoms vary from mild skin and joint involvement to life-threatening renal, hematologic, or central nervous system (CNS) involvement. The most prominent constitutional symptoms of SLE at disease onset include fatigue, fever, and weight loss. Fatigue occurs in a majority of patients, further contributing to pain and psychologic distress.
                        <sup type="ref">[9]</sup> Skin (including the “butterfly rash”) and musculoskeletal symptoms are common symptoms in 80% and 90% of patients, respectively,
                        <sup type="ref">[10]</sup> and fever is present in approximately 50% of patients with active SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[11]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>The diagnosis of SLE is generally based on clinical and laboratory findings. The ACR or Systemic Lupus International Collaborating Clinics (SLICC) Consensus criteria can also be used as further guidance in identifying clinical features of SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[12,13]</sup> ACR criteria require the presence of 4/11 criteria. The SLICC criteria were developed in 2012 and require the presence of 4/17 criteria (at least one clinical criterion for the classification of SLE and 1 of the 6 immunologic criteria) or the presence of biopsy-confirmed lupus nephritis accompanied by antinuclear antibodies (ANA) or anti-double-stranded (dsDNA) antibodies (Table 1).
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 1. Criteria for the Classification of SLE
                        <sup type="ref">[12,13] </sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <th>ACR Criterion</th>
                                <th>Definition</th>
                                <th>SLICC Clinical Criteria*</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Malar rash</td>
                                <td valign="top">Fixed erythema, flat or raised, over the malar eminences, typically sparing the nasolabial folds</td>
                                <td rowspan="10" valign="top">
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Acute cutaneous lupus erythematosus, including “butterfly rash”</li>
                                        <li>Chronic cutaneous lupus erythematosus (eg, localized/generalized discoid lupus erythematosus)</li>
                                        <li>Oral ulcers (on palate and/or nose)</li>
                                        <li>Non-scarring alopecia</li>
                                        <li>Synovitis (≥ 2 joints) or tenderness on palpation (≥ 2 joints) and morning stiffness (≥ 30 min)</li>
                                        <li>Serositis (pleurisy or pericardial pain for &gt; 1 day)</li>
                                        <li>Renal involvement
                
                                            <ul>
                                                <li>Urine protein–to-creatinine ratio (or 24-hour urine protein) representing 500 mg protein/24 hours</li>
                                                <li>
                                                    <strong>OR</strong> red blood cell casts
                                                </li>
                                            </ul>
                                        </li>
                                        <li>Neurologic involvement (eg, seizures, psychosis, myelitis)</li>
                                        <li>Hemolytic anemia</li>
                                        <li>Leukopenia (&lt; 4000/μL) or lymphopenia (&lt; 1000/μL)</li>
                                        <li>Thrombocytopenia (&lt; 100,000/μL)</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Photosensitivity</td>
                                <td valign="top">Skin rash as a result of unusual reaction to sunlight, observed by patient or clinician</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Discoid rash</td>
                                <td valign="top">Erythematosus raised patches with adherent keratotic scaling and follicular plugging; atrophic scarring may occur in older lesions</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Oral ulcers</td>
                                <td valign="top">Oral or nasopharyngeal ulceration, usually painless, observed by a clinician</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Arthritis</td>
                                <td valign="top">Nonerosive arthritis involving 2 or more peripheral joints, characterized by tenderness, swelling, or effusion</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Serositis</td>
                                <td valign="top">Pleuritis
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Convincing history of pleuritic pain or rubbing heard by a clinician or evidence of pleural effusion </li>
                                    </ul>
                                    <strong>OR</strong>
                                    <br/>Pericarditis
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Documented by electrocardiogram (ECG), rub, or evidence of pericardial effusion</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Renal disorder</td>
                                <td valign="top">Persistent proteinuria greater than 500 mg/24 hours or &gt; 3+ if quantitation not performed 
                                    <strong>OR</strong>
                                    <br/>Cellular casts
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>May be red cell, hemoglobin, granular, tubular, or mixed</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Neurologic disorder</td>
                                <td valign="top">Seizures 
                                    <strong>OR</strong> psychosis
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>In the absence of offending drugs or known metabolic derangements (uremia, ketoacidosis, or electrolyte imbalance)</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Hematologic disorder</td>
                                <td valign="top">Hemolytic anemia with reticulocytosis 
                                    <strong>OR</strong>
                                    <br/>Leukopenia
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>&lt; 4000/mm
                                            <sup>3</sup> total on 2 or more occasions 
                                            <strong>OR</strong>
                                        </li>
                                    </ul>
            Lymphopenia

            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>&lt; 1500/mm
                                            <sup>3</sup> on 2 or more occasions 
                                            <strong>OR</strong>
                                        </li>
                                    </ul>
            Thrombocytopenia

            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>&lt; 100,000/mm
                                            <sup>3</sup> (in the absence of offending drugs)
                                        </li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">ANA</td>
                                <td valign="top">Abnormal ANA titer by immunofluorescence or an equivalent assay at any point in time and in the absence of drugs known to be associated with “drug-induced lupus” syndrome</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td valign="top">Immunologic disorders</td>
                                <td valign="top">Anti-DNA: antibody to native DNA in abnormal titer 
                                    <strong>OR</strong>
                                    <br/>Anti-Sm antibodies: presence of antibody to Sm nuclear antigen 
                                    <strong>OR</strong>
                                    <br/>Positive finding of antiphospholipid antibody based on:
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>An abnormal serum level of immunoglobulin G (IgG) or immunoglobulin M (IgM) anticardiolipin antibodies</li>
                                        <li>On a positive test result for lupus anticoagulant using a standard method, or</li>
                                        <li>On a false-positive serologic test for syphilis known to be positive for at least 6 months and confirmed by Treponema pallidum immobilization or fluorescent treponemal antibody absorption test</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                                <td>
                                    <strong>SLICC Immunologic Criteria</strong>
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>ANA level above laboratory reference range</li>
                                        <li>Anti-dsDNA antibodies</li>
                                        <li>Anti-Sm antibodies</li>
                                        <li>Antiphospholipid antibodies (anticardiolipin and anti-β2-glycoprotein I [immunoglobulin A (IgA)-, IgG-, or IgM-] antibodies; false-positive venereal disease research laboratory [VDRL] test)</li>
                                        <li>Low complement (C3, C4, or CH50)</li>
                                        <li>Direct Coombs test (in the absence of hemolytic anemia)</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <blockquote>* Criteria are cumulative and need not be present concurrently.</blockquote>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>The goals of SLE treatment are to control disease activity by decreasing autoimmunity and inflammation, as well as preventing damage to organ systems. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), low-dose glucocorticosteroids, antimalarial medications, immunosuppressants, and biologic agents are the therapeutic mainstays for treating SLE symptoms.
                        <sup type="ref">[14]</sup> NSAIDs are used to treat fever, arthritis/arthralgias and other inflammatory symptoms (serositis). Systemic glucocorticosteroids are used to treat disease activity and flares with the goal to use the lowest possible dose for the shortest period of time. Antimalarial medications such as HCQ are effective in managing SLE by reducing disease activity, decreasing the risk for flares, and improving mortality.
                        <sup type="ref">[15] </sup>Serious adverse effects are extremely rare for antimalarials. Data suggest that antimalarial therapies also improve renal responses when used as adjuvant therapy with mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) and reduce thrombotic events.
                        <sup type="ref">[16]</sup> The 2008 European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) guidelines recommend that all patients with SLE are candidates for antimalarial medications unless there are contraindications. Immunosuppressive agents (eg, azathioprine, MMF, or methotrexate [MTX]) may be considered for treating disease that is not adequately controlled by antimalarials.
                        <sup type="ref">[17]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Lifestyle modifications such as smoking cessation, diet, weight loss, and physical activity are recommended as nonpharmacologic management strategies for patients with SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[14]</sup> Aerobic physical activity in particular has shown particular efficacy for managing symptoms of fatigue and is a recommended lifestyle modification strategy to reduce the risk for cardiovascular disease.
                        <sup type="ref">[8]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1 Continues</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>You conduct a focused medical history, which includes questions about Jeanette’s current medications. When you ask the patient to describe whether she is currently taking her antimalarial medications, she does not respond and instead tells you that her primary care provider prescribed oral prednisone, which she takes when she needs “a little extra” pain relief. Physical examination reveals that the patient has a low-grade fever, tenderness and swelling in several proximal interphalangeal joints and both wrists, and active Raynaud's phenomenon. Jeanette tells you that while she normally needs a nap for an hour or so each day, at the moment she “wants to sleep all day.”</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Raynaud’s phenomenon, a vasospastic process that is triggered by cold exposure, is present in up to 50% of patients with SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[11]</sup> While fever is likely due to SLE in this case, infectious complications can develop in up to 50% of patients with SLE, especially involving the skin, respiratory, and urinary systems.
                        <sup type="ref">[11]</sup> The impaired immune function in SLE predisposes patients to infections, the majority of which are caused by bacteria.
                        <sup type="ref">[18]</sup> Additionally, viral infections including Epstein-Barr virus, cytomegalovirus, and varicella-zoster virus can be challenging to distinguish from active SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[19]</sup> To reduce the risk for morbidity and mortality associated with infections, it is important to keep influenza, 
                        <em>Pneumococcus</em>, hepatitis B virus, and tetanus vaccinations up to date as part of routine patient monitoring.
                        <sup type="ref">[17]</sup> Patients who are immunosuppressed or taking high-dose glucocorticosteroids should not receive live vaccines.
                    </p>
                    <p>Low- and nonadherence to HCQ are common in patients with SLE. Up to 75% of SLE patients do not take their medications as prescribed.
                        <sup type="ref">[20]</sup> Several factors contribute to low medication adherence in SLE, including depression, higher SLE activity, fear of treatment side effects, cognitive deficits, lower socioeconomic status, polypharmacy, and the high cost of medications.
                        <sup type="ref">[21,22]</sup> Patients with increased disease severity may also be less likely to adhere to antimalarial medication due to loss of confidence in treatment efficacy or, conversely, become comfortable about missing, delaying, or reducing antimalarial doses. Patients may also become comfortable with their level of functioning and rationalize new symptoms, as in Jeanette’s case (ie, explaining joint pain in terms of strain from a new physical workout). Low- and nonadherence to medications are significant drivers of poor patient outcomes, including poor disease control, decreased quality of life, and a higher rate of outpatient rheumatology, primary care, and emergency room visits.
                        <sup type="ref">[22]</sup> Conversely, medication adherence in SLE reduces disease activity and risk for flares.
                    </p>
                    <p>Given the complexity of SLE clinical presentations, effective patient-provider communication is a key strategy that can support adherence to pharmacologic therapy. Clinicians should not assume that patients are taking their medications, including antimalarials, as prescribed. It is important to ask specific questions of patients about their adherence to antimalarial therapy, including whether patients have missed or delayed HCQ doses and if so, how often. However, patients might not be forthcoming about low- or nonadherence. Other strategies for determining adherence include measuring plasma HCQ levels. As HCQ has a long elimination half-life, low blood HCQ concentrations represent a feasible marker of low adherence and can be reliably quantified via high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC).
                        <sup type="ref">[21]</sup> Once poor adherence is uncovered, clinicians should discuss patient concerns, such as fears about HCQ side effects. Clinicians should also provide education about safely and effectively using medications, discuss alternative dosing options (eg, reduce the daily number of HCQ doses), and work to build trust and boost patients’ self-efficacy by anticipating and listening to patient concerns about treatment.
                        <sup type="ref">[20]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>4</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Although the presenting pattern of symptoms often prevails throughout the disease course, SLE is characterized by unpredictable periods of exacerbation and remission, in which flares of disease activity contribute to progressive damage and considerable morbidity.
                        <sup type="ref">[23]</sup> Although ANA are evaluated as part of the approach to diagnosis for patients with suspected SLE (Table 2), they are not routinely monitored. Serologic monitoring parameters for lupus disease activity include the presence of anti-dsDNA antibodies and low C3 and/or C4 (Table 2).
                        <sup type="ref">[14]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 2. Clinical and Serologic Disease Activity in SLE
                        <sup type="ref">[24]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>Clinical Disease Activity</th>
                                <th>Serologic Disease Activity</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Inflammatory manifestations
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Mucocutaneous (skin rashes, oral/nasal ulcers, alopecia)</li>
                                        <li>Musculoskeletal (polyarthritis, myositis)</li>
                                        <li>Serositis</li>
                                        <li>Glomerulonephritis</li>
                                        <li>Neurological (cerebritis, seizures, neuropathies, myelitis, others)</li>
                                        <li>GI and ophthalmic manifestations</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                                <td>Autoantibodies
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Anti-dsDNA</li>
                                        <li>Anti-C1q</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Noninflammatory manifestations (autoantibody-mediated)
            
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Hematologic (cytopenia)</li>
                                        <li>Some neurologic manifestations (eg, cognitive dysfunction, psychosis, myasthenia gravis)</li>
                                        <li>aPL-mediated ischemic/microischemic lesions</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                                <td>
                                    <ul>
                                        <li>Decreased serum complement</li>
                                        <li>Increased complement split products</li>
                                    </ul>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Assessment of disease activity, organ involvement, risk factors (ie, infection, cardiovascular disease), and complications is an important aspect of the standard of care for monitoring and managing patients with SLE, and new clinical manifestations such as arthritis or skin lesions should be noted and documented.
                        <sup type="ref">[14,17] </sup>EULAR and the British Society for Rheumatology guidelines recommend assessing patients with inactive disease at 6- to 12-month intervals for complete blood count (CBC) with differential, erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR), C-reactive protein (CRP), serum albumin, serum creatinine (or estimated glomerular filtration rate [eGFR]), and urinalysis and urine protein/creatinine ratio.
                        <sup type="ref">[14,25]</sup> These routine laboratory parameters are also recommended for patients presenting with evidence of active disease. Serum evidence of leukopenia, anemia, or thrombocytopenia may reflect active disease, while ESR and CRP elevations can also reflect increased disease activity and accrued damage; however, elevations in acute phase reactants are common in patients with SLE and might not be reliable markers of disease activity.
                        <sup type="ref">[26,27] </sup>Patients with active disease are evaluated as frequently as required by the active manifestation being treated, on average every 1 to 3 months.
                    </p>
                    <p>Complement levels are also associated with active disease. Low C3/C4 and/or elevated C3/C4 activation products may indicate active lupus/lupus nephritis, which is a severe complication of SLE that increases morbidity, including end-stage renal disease, and mortality.
                        <sup type="ref">[11]</sup> There is a lifetime prevalence of kidney involvement for approximately 50% of SLE patients.
                        <sup type="ref">[2]</sup> Assessment to exclude kidney involvement should include urinalysis with examination for urinary sediment, serum creatinine, eGFR, and protein-to-creatinine ratio to assess severity of glomerular disease.
                        <sup type="ref">[17]</sup> Increased serum titer of anti-dsDNA and low complement levels (ie, CH50, C3, C4) are indicative of flare.
                        <sup type="ref">[23]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>5</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Flares are common occurrences throughout the course of SLE and can result in organ damage. Although accepted definitions of flare are inconsistent, they are broadly defined as measurable increases in or worsening of disease activity in one or more organ systems.
                        <sup type="ref">[29]</sup> Flares are typically categorized as mild, moderate, or severe, and high SLEDAI scores are predictive of SLE damage accumulation and mortality (Table 3).
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 3. Examples of Mild, Moderate, Severe Flares
                        <sup type="ref">[25]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>Mild</th>
                                <th>Moderate</th>
                                <th>Severe</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>SLEDAI &lt; 6
                                    <br/>
                                    <br/>And/or
                                    <br/>
                                    <br/>Clinically stable with no life-threatening organ involvement (eg, arthralgia, fatigue, mucocutaneous lesions, recurrent episodes of ulcers, mild pleuritis)
                                </td>
                                <td>SLEDAI 6-12
                                    <br/>
                                    <br/>And/or
                                    <br/>
                                    <br/>More serious manifestations including fever, lupus-related rash, cutaneous vasculitis, alopecia with scalp inflammation, arthritis, pleurisy, pericarditis
                                </td>
                                <td>SLEDAI &gt; 12
                                    <br/>
                                    <br/>And/or
                                    <br/>
                                    <br/>Organ- or life-threatening (eg, widespread rash, myositis, severe pleurisy, and/or pericarditis, ascites, enteritis, myelopathy, psychosis, acute confusion, optic neuritis)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Predictors of flare include young age at SLE diagnosis (&lt; 25 years), lupus nephritis prior to baseline visit, and immunosuppressive treatment for SLE.
                        <sup type="ref">[30]</sup> Based on data from the belimumab trials, predictors of moderate-to-severe flares in patients being treated with standard therapies included renal, neurologic, or vasculitic involvement, elevated anti-dsDNA, or high B lymphocyte stimulator levels, and low C3.
                        <sup type="ref">[23]</sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Several instruments have been developed to assess disease activity and flare. Several versions of the SLEDAI are in use: the Safety of Estrogens in Systemic Lupus Erythematosus National Assessment (SELENA)-SLEDAI (an instrument specific to flare measurement), SLEDAI-2K, and Hybrid-SLEDAI. It is important to be mindful of the version of the SLEDAI you are using as your score is likely to be different depending on the instrument used. In addition to SLEDAI, other instruments used in clinical trials and in research include the British Isles Lupus Assessment Group (BILAG) and the Revised Systemic Lupus Activity Measure (SLAM-R). However, these instruments are complicated to use and difficult to score and have not been adopted in practice.
                        <sup type="ref">[29]</sup> Moreover, physician-completed indices typically assess SLE disease activity via clinical and/or laboratory findings and not the extent to which the disease impacts patient health-related quality of life and functioning. Patient-reported outcomes (PRO) measures provide additional information concerning disease impact on health-related quality of life and functioning that are not captured by physician assessment.
                        <sup type="ref">[31]</sup> PRO instruments used in research settings include the Medical Outcomes Study Short Form 36 (SF-36) and SLE-specific tools such as Lupus Quality of Life (LupusQoL) and LupusPRO. The Lupus Impact Tracker
                        <a href=""></a>(LIT) is a short tool that can be integrated into clinical practice to assess disease impact on patients and support constructive dialog with patients about treatment planning and disease management.
                        <sup type="ref">[32]</sup> While symptoms of mild flare can be subtle and may require minimal or no intervention to control, severe flares are clinically significant and require a change in treatment.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1 Continues</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Laboratory findings (Table 4) and disease activity assessment of the patient using SLEDAI indicates worsening disease activity. Your diagnosis is SLE with an arthritis flare and you recommend a short course of oral prednisone 10 mg/day. You also suggest that Jeanette keep a daily diary of her symptoms to monitor fatigue and pain. You see Jeanette again for follow-up at 4 weeks and again at 8 weeks after initiation of prednisone; however, at 8 weeks, neither the patient’s symptoms nor disease activity measures have improved. You increase steroid dosing to 20 mg/day, and after 3 months, there is some improvement but steroid toxicities start to become apparent. </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 4: Relevant Laboratory Results</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>Laboratory Test</th>
                                <th>Results</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Hemoglobin</td>
                                <td>12.2 (11.5-15.5 g/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>White blood cell count</td>
                                <td>5.3 (4-11 x10
                                    <sup>9</sup>/L)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Platelet count</td>
                                <td>180 (150-450 x10
                                    <sup>9</sup>/L)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>ESR</td>
                                <td>33 (&lt; 20 mm/h)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>CRP</td>
                                <td>14 (&lt; 5 mg/L)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>eGFR</td>
                                <td>&gt; 60 ( &gt; 90 mL/min/1.73m
                                    <sup>2</sup>)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>C3</td>
                                <td>72 (80-180 mg/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>C4</td>
                                <td>6 (10 -45 mg/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>dsDNA</td>
                                <td>525 (&lt; 30 IU/mL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Urinalysis</td>
                                <td>Without abnormalities</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>6</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Patients with moderate SLE, especially with high anti-dsDNA and low complement, who do not respond to HCQ and short-course prednisone, may require additional therapy. MTX is a disease-modifying antirheumatic drug (DMARD) approved for treating rheumatoid arthritis (RA). Although not approved for the treatment of SLE, it can be used to alleviate joint pain and swelling in mild SLE, as well as lupus skin rashes.
                        <sup type="ref">[33]</sup> The persistent serologic unrest evident in Jeanette’s case makes MTX not an ideal therapeutic option for this patient. Abatacept is currently approved for RA and has shown some efficacy in patients with SLE refractory to conventional therapies but is also not US Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved for this indication,
                        <sup type="ref">[34]</sup> although clinical trials investigating abatacept in SLE arthritis are currently ongoing. Use of etanercept in SLE is limited by concerns of increasing disease activity.
                        <sup type="ref">[36]</sup> Intravenous (IV) or subcutaneous belimumab is an anti-B-lymphocyte stimulator (BlyS; also known as anti-B-cell activating factor [BAFF] or anti-CD257) monoclonal antibody that is FDA approved as add-on therapy for adults with persistently active SLE with skin and/or joint disease that do not respond to standard therapies. There are currently no data comparing the effectiveness of belimumab to other agents in SLE, nor are there data to establish the most effective combination strategy.
                    </p>
                    <p>Immunosuppressant therapy is used in more moderate-to-severe nonrenal cases of SLE when high-dose corticosteroids or antimalarial medications have failed to control disease activity or to reduce flares. Current options include cyclophosphamide, azathioprine, and MMF. These agents exert suppressant effects on the immune system by reducing T-cell and B-cell proliferation as well as via DNA and RNA disruption.
                        <sup type="ref">[35]</sup> Cyclophosphamide is not approved for SLE but is typically used as induction treatment for severe SLE and can be followed by other maintenance therapies such as azathioprine or MMF.
                        <sup type="ref">[36] </sup>Although MMF has not been specially evaluated in nonrenal lupus, accumulating data suggest that MMF combined with steroids can reduce moderate and severe SLE disease activity as well as renal and nonrenal flares.
                        <sup type="ref">[19,37] </sup>These agents are generally well tolerated, with side effects including myelosuppression, hepatotoxicity, renal dysfunction, increased risk of infection, and cancer.
                    </p>
                    <p>Cyclophosphamide has been associated with amenorrhea, especially with high doses, and risk for infertility.
                        <sup type="ref">[38]</sup> MMF is better tolerated and less toxic than cyclophosphamide.
                        <sup type="ref">[39,40] </sup>In fact, due to its less severe side effect profile, the 2012 ACR Clinical Practice Guidelines for Lupus Nephritis established MMF as the preferred induction agent compared with cyclophosphamide for patients in whom fertility preservation is a major consideration.
                        <sup type="ref">[41]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>7</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Patient perspective is a critical consideration in the context of treatment planning and flare management. Clinicians and patients need to work together to make decisions about appropriate treatment strategies based on clinical evidence that balances risks and expected outcomes with patient preferences and values.
                        <sup type="ref">[42]</sup> As data continue to accumulate on treat-to-target strategies with the goal to achieve the lupus low disease activity state (LLDAS) (Figure 1), physicians might start to consider LLDAS and remission as the correct targets aimed at decreasing long-term morbidity and mortality in SLE. 
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Figure 1. Lupus Low Disease Activity State
                        <sup type="ref">[43] </sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>
                        <img src="professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/371/902371-fig1.jpg"/>
                    </p>
                    <p></p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 1 Conclusion</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Jeanette would prefer to avoid injectable therapies (IV or subcutaneous) at this time. You initiate treatment with MMF, 1000 mg twice daily. At follow-up, Jeanette is tolerating her medication and both her symptoms and SLEDAI scoring have improved. When you see her at future follow-up visits, in addition to monitoring therapeutic drug levels, you provide additional education about strategies for managing fatigue and avoiding sun exposure and periodically assess her general education needs on SLE.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2: Patient History</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table align="left" border="1" bordercolor="#b3b3b3" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="0" style="margin-right: 20px;">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="center">
                                    <img alt="" border="0" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/content/article/902/371/902371-patient2.png?interpolation=lanczos-none&amp;resize=200:150"/>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <p style="min-height: 230px;">Rocío is 51-year-old female patient with a 9-year history of SLE who has moved to a new city for employment and is registering with a new rheumatologist. At intake, you conduct a review of systems, physical examination, medical history, and current medication history, including vaccination status, which reveal that the patient is currently not taking antimalarial medications. Rocío tells you that she took HCQ “for a while, a few years ago” but was concerned about treatment side effects and stopped taking the medication. She also took azathioprine and MMF but could not tolerate either because of gastrointestinal side effects. Her primary care physician has been prescribing high-dose glucocorticosteroids for the last couple of years, and Rocío says that “the more prednisone she takes, the better she feels.” Her chief complaint today is moon face.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>8</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Although there are few randomized controlled trials (RCTs) to support the use of glucocorticosteroids in suppressing SLE inflammation, these agents offer potent therapy for treating active disease and are commonly used to manage many SLE manifestations. Studies suggest that up to 80% of SLE patients have been exposed to glucocorticosteroids and that a majority are treated long term.
                        <sup type="ref">[46,47] </sup>However, oral corticosteroid use is associated with a wide spectrum of serious side effects in patients with SLE (Table 5). Glucocorticosteroids have also been consistently shown to exacerbate the effects of active disease on SLE damage accrual and contribute to irreversible damage in patients with SLE, which is a major predictor of morbidity and mortality.
                        <sup type="ref">[48] </sup> Recent data have also suggested that doses of glucocorticoids over 6 mg/day are associated with an increased risk of side effects.
                        <sup type="ref">[45]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 5. Adverse Effects Associated With Corticosteroid Use
                        <sup type="ref">[36]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>Potential Adverse Effects</th>
                                <th>Suggested Monitoring Parameters</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Weight gain, hypertension, hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia, osteoporosis, osteonecrosis, cataracts, edema, hypokalemia, muscle weakness, growth suppression, increased infection risk, glaucoma, psychologic and behavioral disturbances, Cushingoid effects</td>
                                <td>Baseline blood pressure, bone density, glucose, potassium, lipid panel, glucose every 3 to 6 months, annual lipid panel, bone density</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2 Continues</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>History further reveals that Rocío has been progressively increasing steroid doses and has gained “a lot of weight.” She has a family history of diabetes, and her blood pressure is 132/83 mm Hg.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>9</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <TOCLabel/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Patients with SLE have an increased risk of fracture, which occurs in 9% to 12% of patients.
                        <sup type="ref">[51] </sup>Bone mineral density declines rapidly within the first 3 months of glucocorticosteroid treatment. Therefore, identification and treatment of bone mineral loss are important for fracture prevention. ACR guidelines recommend bone density screening with dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan and vitamin D level screening in patients older than 30 years who are taking glucocorticosteroids for ≥ 3 months.
                        <sup type="ref">[52] </sup>These guidelines additionally recommend that patients maintain a total calcium intake of 1000-1200 mg/day and vitamin D 600-800 IU/day. Antiresorptive therapy (eg, bisphosphonates, selective estrogen receptor modulators, denosumab, estrogen, and calcium) slows bone turnover by increasing resorption and decreasing fracture rate by varying degrees. Treatment of glucocorticosteroid-induced osteoporosis with bisphosphonates is recommended for patients who are at moderate to high risk for fractures.
                        <sup type="ref">[52] </sup>Patients with SLE are also at increased risk for cardiovascular disease compared with an age-matched general population, with higher prevalence of risk factors such as hypertension and diabetes mellitus, total cholesterol, triglycerides, and hypertension.
                        <sup type="ref">[52] </sup>Glucocorticosteroids may also be independently associated with higher risk for cardiovascular disease.
                        <sup type="ref">[53,54] </sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2 Continues</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>You order lupus labs, a bone density scan, lipid panel, and HbA1C test (Table 6).</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 6: Laboratory Results</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>Laboratory Test</th>
                                <th>Results</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Hemoglobin</td>
                                <td>13.4 (11.5-15.5 g/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>White blood cell count</td>
                                <td>8.0 (4-11 x10
                                    <sup>9</sup>/L)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Platelet count</td>
                                <td>205 (150-450 x10
                                    <sup>9</sup>/L)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>ESR</td>
                                <td>5 (&lt; 20 mm/hr)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>CRP</td>
                                <td>0.3 (&lt; 3 mg/L)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>eGFR</td>
                                <td>&gt; 60 (&gt; 90 mL/min/1.73m
                                    <sup>2</sup>)
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>C3</td>
                                <td>131 (80-180 mg/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>C4</td>
                                <td>20 (10-45 mg/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>dsDNA</td>
                                <td>45 (&lt; 30 IU/mL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Urinalysis</td>
                                <td>No abnormalities</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>T score</td>
                                <td>-2.5</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>Cholesterol</td>
                                <td>200 mg/dL (&lt;200 mg/dL)</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>HbA1C</td>
                                <td>6.0% (pre-diabetes 5.7%-6.4%)</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>When Rocío returns to discuss her test results, you discuss steps to address osteoporosis and manage her pre-diabetes. You prescribe bisphosphonates, provide education on lifestyle modification (eg, smoking cessation, alcohol reduction, weight loss), and recommend strategies for increasing vitamin D and calcium intake. You also guide Rocío toward tools and smartphone apps she can use to track her symptoms, such as the ACR’s Lupus Companion and the US Department of Health and Human Services Lupus Symptom Tracker.
                        <sup type="ref">[55,56] </sup>A variety of tools can be used to engage patients in self-management and promote shared decision making and may improve patient-provider communication and outcomes.
                        <sup type="ref">[42]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>10</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Steroid-sparing strategies to achieve disease control involve low-dose glucocorticosteroids combined with other agents such as antimalarial and immunosuppressive therapies. Glucocorticosteroids should be tapered to the lowest dose necessary to control disease activity; however, there is little evidence to guide tapering strategies in SLE. Most recommendations are based on expert opinion, and in the absence of widely accepted tapering protocols, tapering can be challenging. A 2013 review of studies on tapering regimens in RA patients found that glucocorticosteroid tapering was less successful in patients with 6 years of disease duration, with success rates higher for patients with less than 2 years of duration (31% vs 78%).
                        <sup type="ref">[58] </sup>
                    </p>
                    <p>Tapering regimens should take into consideration the patient’s general health status, levels of disease activity, and the particular glucocorticosteroid regimen being used. Published tapering protocols in RA suggest either switching to alternate-day therapy (eg, giving the entire prednisone dose on alternate days) or gradually lowering the daily dose every 10 to 14 days.
                        <sup type="ref">[59] </sup>However, SLE symptoms may recur during glucocorticosteroid tapering alongside symptoms of glucocorticosteroid withdrawal such as arthralgia and myalgia. Finally, patients and physicians like steroids because they represent a “quick fix” and can have a mood-elevating effect; therefore, patients need considerable support to navigate the steroid-tapering process.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2 Continues</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>In addition to tapering prednisone, you restart HCQ and educate Rocío on how to differentiate steroid withdrawal symptoms from lupus flare symptoms. When she returns 6 weeks following initiation of prednisone taper, her repeat blood work shows low complement, higher dsDNA, and worsening serologic activity. Rocío complains of worse arthralgia and arthritis, and physical examination reveals swollen proximal intraphalangeal joints. Rocío tells you she has started to increase her steroid dose again.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form>11</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Discussion</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Symptoms, signs, and laboratory tests suggest unsuccessful tapering, which potentiates the risk of flare for Rocío. Because she was previously unable to tolerate other immunosuppressants, therapies with other mechanisms of action are warranted. Efficacy and safety data for belimumab, which inhibits B-cell survival and differentiation, indicate that it is likely to be the most effective treatment option for patients with severe disease that does not respond to standard therapy with steroids or immunosuppressive agents.</p>
                    <p>Three phase 3 trials have evaluated the efficacy and safety of belimumab in patients with SLE using SELENA-SLEDAI and SLE Responder Index (SRI) scores. The SRI adds the BILAG and physician’s global assessment (PGA) to the SLEDAI to ensure that improvements in SLEDAI were not achieved at the expense of the overall condition of the patient and/or worsening in other organ/systems. Two trials (BLISS 52 and BLISS 76) involving 1,686 patients in total over 52 and 76 weeks of treatment demonstrated that treatment with belimumab improved SRI response vs placebo, reduced disease activity, and decreased flares.
                        <sup type="ref">[60,61] </sup>In a third phase 3 trial (n = 839), treatment with subcutaneous belimumab combined with standard of care similarly reduced disease activity and reduced flare risk.
                        <sup type="ref">[62] </sup>Belimumab was well tolerated in these trials. Upper respiratory tract and urinary tract infections, arthralgia, headaches, fatigue, and nausea were the most commonly reported adverse events. Serious infusion reactions and infections were rare. Pooled analysis of BLISS 52 and BLISS 76 affirmed the benefit of belimumab compared with standard therapy in patients with higher disease activity (SELENA-SLEDAI ≥ 10), positive anti-dsDNA antibodies, low complement, or glucocorticosteroid treatment at baseline.
                        <sup type="ref">[63] </sup>These trials and post-marketing studies have also demonstrated a steroid-sparing benefit with belimumab. Approximately half of patients in BLISS 52 achieved a sustained reduction in prednisone use to &lt; 7.5 mg/day with belimumab,
                        <sup type="ref">[60]</sup> and long-term post-marketing observational cohort data similarly affirm the steroid-reducing benefit of belimumab.
                        <sup type="ref">[64] </sup>Belimumab is typically administered via an IV route; however, the subcutaneous option was FDA approved in 2017, which allows patients to self-administer therapy in a once-weekly dose.
                    </p>
                    <p>MTX is also a potential option for Rocío. Clinical trial and observational data suggest that patients with inflammatory arthritis related to lupus can benefit from treatment with MTX.
                        <sup type="ref">[65] </sup>MTX has also been shown to reduce glucocorticosteroid doses in patients with SLE compared with control groups. Adverse events associated with MTX include gastrointestinal symptoms, hepatoxicity, and infections. Finally, data from open observation trials, registries, and 2 phase 3 RCTs have shown that rituximab is efficacious in treating articular, mucocutaneous, and hematologic manifestations of SLE, as well as lupus nephritis (Table 7).
                        <sup type="ref">[66-68] </sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Table 7. Main Results of 2 Rituximab (RTX) RCTs in SLE
                        <sup type="ref">[66]</sup>
                    </p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <table class="inline_data_table">
                        <tbody>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <th>Trial</th>
                                <th>Inclusion</th>
                                <th>Main Results at 52 Weeks</th>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>EXPLORER
                                    <br/>(n = 257, 42% Asian, Hispanic, African American)
                                </td>
                                <td>≥ 1 BILAG A (except severe or organ-threatening disease) or ≥ 2 BILAG B</td>
                                <td>Major clinical response:
                                    <br/>▪ RTX = 12% vs placebo 16%
                                    <br/>Partial clinical response:
                                    <br/>▪ RTX = 17% vs placebo = 13%
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr valign="top">
                                <td>LUNAR
                                    <br/>(n = 144, 69% Asian, Hispanic, African American)
                                </td>
                                <td>Biopsy-confirmed active class III/IV lupus nephritis with urine protein/creatinine ratio &gt; 1.0</td>
                                <td>Complete renal response:
                                    <br/>▪ RTX = 26% vs placebo = 31%
                                    <br/>Partial renal response:
                                    <br/>▪ RTX = 31% vs placebo = 15
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    <blockquote>Mok CC. 
                        <em>Int J Rheum Dis</em>. 2015;18:154-163. © 2014 Asia Pacific League of Associations for Rheumatology and Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd.
                    </blockquote>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Clinical improvement in rituximab-treated African American and Hispanic SLE patients was better than for Caucasian patients.
                        <sup type="ref">[68]</sup> A systematic review of rituximab in patients with active disease who were refractory to corticosteroids and immunosuppressive agents also concluded that rituximab improved disease activity, complement levels, dsDNA, and arthritis and reduced steroid use.
                        <sup type="ref">[69]</sup> This agent offers a potential treatment option for patients with SLE symptoms that have not responded to conventional regimens, as well as for patients with contraindications or intolerance to standard therapies.
                        <sup type="ref">[66]</sup> Adverse events associated with rituximab include infusion reactions, neutropenia, and infections.
                    </p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Case 2 Conclusion</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>Six months after initiating therapy with IV belimumab, she has been able to taper steroids to 5 mg and will continue the taper, her moon face symptoms are resolving, and laboratory tests are much improved. You discuss the option of switching to subcutaneous belimumab, how long she can expect this response to last, and side effects she should be aware of. To ensure you and Rocío manage her SLE together as effectively as possible and, if necessary, modify therapies, it will be important for her to continue monitoring her symptoms, be aware of changes in weight, maintain a well-balanced diet, and incorporate physical activity into everyday life.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header>
                    <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
                </subsec_header>
                <subsec_content>
                    <p>What did you learn from this activity? Please click on the “Next” button to proceed to a brief survey to see how your knowledge improved after the education. You can also see how your answers compare with those of your peers.</p>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header>
                <p>Educational Impact Challenge</p>
            </sec_header>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro/>
                <slide_grp>
                    <sec_img/>
                    <sec_label/>
                    <sec_caption/>
                    <sec_txt/>
                    <sec_alt_txt/>
                    <qna_form>12</qna_form>
                </slide_grp>
                <qna_form>12</qna_form>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label/>
        <toc_type>Default</toc_type>
        <pg_footnotes/>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <slide_intro/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
    </toc_element>
    <toc_element>
        <toc_label>
            <p>References</p>
        </toc_label>
        <toc_type>References</toc_type>
        <sec_element>
            <sec_header/>
            <subsec_element>
                <subsec_header/>
                <subsec_content>
                    <ol>
                        <li>Greco CM, Rudy TE, Manzi S. Adaptation to chronic pain in systemic lupus erythematosus: applicability of the multidimensional pain inventory. 
                            <em>Pain Med. </em>2003;4:39-50.
                        </li>
                        <li>Helmick CG, Felson DT, Lawrence RC, et al. Estimates of the prevalence of arthritis and other rheumatic conditions in the United States. Part I. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheumatol. </em>2008;58:15-25.
                        </li>
                        <li>Lim SS, Bayakly AR, Helmick CG, et al. The incidence and prevalence of systemic lupus erythematosus, 2002-2004: The Georgia Lupus Registry. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheumatol. </em>2014;66:357-368.
                        </li>
                        <li>Stojan G, Petri M. Epidemiology of systemic lupus erythematosus: an update. 
                            <em>Curr Opin Rheumatol. </em>2018;30:144-150.
                        </li>
                        <li>Izmirly PM, Wan I, Sahl S, et al. The Incidence and prevalence of systemic lupus erythematosus in New York County (Manhattan), New York: The Manhattan Lupus Surveillance Program. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheumatol. </em>2017;69:2006-2017.
                        </li>
                        <li>Dall'Era M, Cisternas MG, Snipes K, et al. The incidence and prevalence of systemic lupus erythematosus in San Francisco County, California: The California Lupus Surveillance Project. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheumatol. </em>2017;69:1996-2005.
                        </li>
                        <li>Somers EC, Marder W, Cagnoli P, et al. Population-based incidence and prevalence of systemic lupus erythematosus: the Michigan Lupus Epidemiology and Surveillance program. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheumatol. </em>2014;66:369-378.
                        </li>
                        <li>Yuen HK, Cunningham MA. Optimal management of fatigue in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus: a systematic review. 
                            <em>Ther Clin Risk Manag. </em>2014;10:775-786.
                        </li>
                        <li>Jump RL, Robinson ME, Armstrong AE, et al. Fatigue in systemic lupus erythematosus: contributions of disease activity, pain, depression, and perceived social support. 
                            <em>J Rheumatol. </em>2005;32:1699-1705.
                        </li>
                        <li>Rothfield N, Sontheimer RD, Bernstein M, et al. Lupus erythematosus: systemic and cutaneous manifestations. 
                            <em>Clin Dermatol</em>. 2006;24:348-362.
                        </li>
                        <li>Cervera R, Khamashta MA, Font J, et al. Morbidity and mortality in systemic lupus erythematosus during a 10-year period: a comparison of early and late manifestations in a cohort of 1,000 patients. 
                            <em>Medicine. </em>2003;82:299-308.
                        </li>
                        <li>Tan EM, Cohen AS, Fries JF, et al. The 1982 revised criteria for the classification of systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>1982;25:1271-1277.
                        </li>
                        <li>Petri M, Orbai AM, Alarcon GS, et al. Derivation and validation of the Systemic Lupus International Collaborating Clinics classification criteria for systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2012;64:2677-2686.
                        </li>
                        <li>Bertsias G, Ioannidis JPA, Boletis J, et al. EULAR recommendations for the management of systemic lupus erythematosus. Report of a Task Force of the EULAR Standing Committee for International Clinical Studies Including Therapeutics. 
                            <em>Ann Rheum Dis. </em>2008;67:195-205.
                        </li>
                        <li>Mok CC. Mycophenolate mofetil for non-renal manifestations of systemic lupus erythematosus: a systematic review. 
                            <em>Scand J Rheum. </em>2007;36:329-337.
                        </li>
                        <li>Akhavan PS, Su J, Lou W, et al. The early protective effect of hydroxychloroquine on the risk of cumulative damage in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>J Rheumatol. </em>2013;40:831-841.
                        </li>
                        <li>Mosca M, Tani C, Aringer M, et al. European League Against Rheumatism recommendations for monitoring patients with systemic lupus erythematosus in clinical practice and in observational studies. 
                            <em>Ann Rheum Dis. </em>2010;69:1269-1274.
                        </li>
                        <li>Cuchacovich R, Gedalia A. Pathophysiology and clinical spectrum of infections in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Rheum Dis Clin North Am. </em>2009;35:75-93.
                        </li>
                        <li>Lam N-CL GM, Bienek ML. Systemic lupus erythematosus: Primary care approach to diagnosis and management. 
                            <em>Am Fam Phys. </em>2016;94:284-294.
                        </li>
                        <li>Mehat P, Atiquzzaman M, Esdaile JM, et al. Medication nonadherence in systemic lupus erythematosus: a systematic review. 
                            <em>Arthritis Care Res. </em>2017;69:1706-1713.
                        </li>
                        <li>Costedoat-Chalumeau N, Pouchot J, Guettrot-Imbert G, et al. Adherence to treatment in systemic lupus erythematosus patients. 
                            <em>Best Pract Res Clin Rheumatol. </em>2013;27:329-340.
                        </li>
                        <li>Feldman CH, Yazdany J, Guan H, et al. Medication nonadherence is associated with increased subsequent acute care utilization among Medicaid beneficiaries with systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Arthritis Care Res. </em>2015;67:1712-1721.
                        </li>
                        <li>Petri MA, van Vollenhoven RF, Buyon J, et al. Baseline predictors of systemic lupus erythematosus flares: data from the combined placebo groups in the phase III belimumab trials. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2013;65:2143-2153.
                        </li>
                        <li>Doria A, Gatto M, Zen M, et al. Optimizing outcome in SLE: treating-to-target and definition of treatment goals. 
                            <em>Autoimmunity Reviews. </em>2014;13:770-777.
                        </li>
                        <li>Gordon C, Amissah-Arthur MB, Gayed M, et al. The British Society for Rheumatology guideline for the management of systemic lupus erythematosus in adults. 
                            <em>Rheumatology. </em>2018;57:e1-e45.
                        </li>
                        <li>Lee SS, Singh S, Link K, et al. High-sensitivity C-reactive protein as an associate of clinical subsets and organ damage in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Semin Arthritis Rheum. </em>2008;38:41-54.
                        </li>
                        <li>Vila LM, Alarcon GS, McGwin G, Jr., et al. Systemic lupus erythematosus in a multiethnic cohort (LUMINA): XXIX. Elevation of erythrocyte sedimentation rate is associated with disease activity and damage accrual. 
                            <em>J Rheumatol. </em>2005;32:2150-2155.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ibanez D, Gladman DD, Touma Z, et al. Optimal frequency of visits for patients with systemic lupus erythematosus to measure disease activity over time. 
                            <em>J Rheumatol. </em>2011;38:60-63.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ruperto N, Hanrahan LM, Alarcon GS, et al. International consensus for a definition of disease flare in lupus. 
                            <em>Lupus. </em>2011;20:453-462.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ines L, Duarte C, Silva RS, et al. Identification of clinical predictors of flare in systemic lupus erythematosus patients: a 24-month prospective cohort study. 
                            <em>Rheumatology. </em>2014;53:85-89.
                        </li>
                        <li>Mahieu M, Yount S, Ramsey-Goldman R. Patient-reported outcomes in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Rheum Dis Clin North Am. </em>2016;42:253-263.
                        </li>
                        <li>Jolly M, Kosinski M, Garris CP, et al. Prospective validation of the lupus impact tracker: a patient-completed tool for clinical practice to evaluate the impact of systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2016;68:1422-1431.
                        </li>
                        <li>Sakthiswary R, Suresh E. Methotrexate in systemic lupus erythematosus: a systematic review of its efficacy. 
                            <em>Lupus. </em>2014;23:225-235.
                        </li>
                        <li>Danion F, Rosine N, Belkhir R, et al. Efficacy of abatacept in systemic lupus erythematosus: a retrospective analysis of 11 patients with refractory disease. 
                            <em>Lupus. </em>2016;25:1440-1447.
                        </li>
                        <li>Maidhof W, Hilas O. Lupus: an overview of the disease and management options. 
                            <em>P T. </em>2012;37:240-249.
                        </li>
                        <li>Davis LS, Reimold AM. Research and therapeutics-traditional and emerging therapies in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Rheumatology. </em>2017;56:i100-i113.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ginzler EM, Wofsy D, Isenberg D, et al. Nonrenal disease activity following mycophenolate mofetil or intravenous cyclophosphamide as induction treatment for lupus nephritis: findings in a multicenter, prospective, randomized, open-label, parallel-group clinical trial. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2010;62:211-221.
                        </li>
                        <li>Boumpas DT, Austin HA 3rd, Vaughan EM, et al. Risk for sustained amenorrhea in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus receiving intermittent pulse cyclophosphamide therapy. 
                            <em>Ann Intern Med</em>. 1993;119:366-369.
                        </li>
                        <li>Appel GB, Contreras G, Dooley MA, et al. Mycophenolate mofetil versus cyclophosphamide for induction treatment of lupus nephritis. 
                            <em>J Am Soc Nephrol</em>. 2009;20:1103-1112.
                        </li>
                        <li>Henderson L, Masson P, Craig JC, et al. Treatment for lupus nephritis. 
                            <em>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</em>. 2012;12:CD002922
                        </li>
                        <li>Hahn BH, McMahon MA, Wilkinson A, et al. American College of Rheumatology guidelines for screening, treatment, and management of lupus nephritis. 
                            <em>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken).</em> 2012;64:797-808.
                        </li>
                        <li>Qu H, Shewchuk RM, Alarcon G, et al. Mapping perceptions of lupus medication decision-making facilitators: the importance of patient context. 
                            <em>Arthritis Care Res. </em>2016;68:1787-1794.
                            <p>43. Franklyn K, Lau CS, Navarra SV, et al. Definition and initial validation of a Lupus Low Disease Activity State (LLDAS). 
                                <em>Ann Rheum Dis. </em>2016;75:1615-1621.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>Strehl C, Bijlsma JWJ, de Wit M, et al. Defining conditions where long-term glucocorticoid treatment has an acceptably low level of harm to facilitate implementation of existing recommendations: viewpoints from an EULAR task force. 
                            <em>Ann Rheum Dis.</em> 2016;75:952-957.
                        </li>
                        <li>Al Sawah S, Zhang X, Zhu B, et al. Effect of corticosteroid use by dose on the risk of developing organ damage over time in systemic lupus erythematosus-the Hopkins Lupus Cohort. 
                            <em>Lupus Sci Med</em>. 2015;2:e000066.
                        </li>
                        <li>Nikpour M, Urowitz MB, Ibanez D, et al. Frequency and determinants of flare and persistently active disease in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2009;61:1152-1158.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ruiz-Arruza I, Ugarte A, Cabezas-Rodriguez I, et al. Glucocorticoids and irreversible damage in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Rheumatology. </em>2014;53:1470-1476.
                        </li>
                        <li>Ruiz-Irastorza G, Danza A, Khamashta M. Glucocorticoid use and abuse in SLE. 
                            <em>Rheumatology. </em>2012;51:1145-1153.
                        </li>
                        <li>Pineau CA, Urowitz MB, Fortin PJ, et al. Osteoporosis in systemic lupus erythematosus: factors associated with referral for bone mineral density studies, prevalence of osteoporosis and factors associated with reduced bone density. 
                            <em>Lupus. </em>2004;13:436-441.
                        </li>
                        <li>Apostolopoulos D, Morand EF. It hasn't gone away: the problem of glucocorticoid use in lupus remains. 
                            <em>Rheumatology. </em>2017;56:i114-i122.
                        </li>
                        <li>Panopalis P, Yazdany J. Bone health in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Curr Rheumatol Rep. </em>2009;11:177-184.
                        </li>
                        <li>Buckley L, Guyatt G, Fink HA, et al. 2017 American College of Rheumatology Guideline for the prevention and treatment of glucocorticoid-induced osteoporosis. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2017;69:1521-1537.
                        </li>
                        <li>Karp I, Abrahamowicz M, Fortin PR, et al. Recent corticosteroid use and recent disease activity: independent determinants of coronary heart disease risk factors in systemic lupus erythematosus? 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2008;59:169-175.
                        </li>
                        <li>Magder LS, Petri M. Incidence of and risk factors for adverse cardiovascular events among patients with systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Am J Epidemiol</em>. 2012;176:708-719.
                        </li>
                        <li>Lupus Symptom Tracker. https://www.womenshealth.gov/files/assets/docs/charts-checklists-guides/lupus-symptom-tracker.pdf. Accessed September 18. 2018.</li>
                        <li>The Lupus Companion
                            <sup>©</sup>. https://thelupusinitiative.org/patients-caregivers/resources/the-lupus-companion/. Accessed September 18. 2018.
                        </li>
                        <li>American College of Rheumatology. Guidelines for referral and management of systemic lupus erythematosus in adults. American College of Rheumatology Ad Hoc Committee on systemic lupus erythematosus guidelines. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>1999;42:1785-1796.
                        </li>
                        <li>Volkmann ER, Rezai S, Tarp S, et al. We still don't know how to taper glucocorticoids in rheumatoid arthritis, and we can do better. 
                            <em>J Rheumatol. </em>2013;40:1646-1649.
                        </li>
                        <li>Nelson AM, Conn DL. Series on pharmacology in practice. 9. Glucocorticoids in rheumatic disease. 
                            <em>Mayo Clinic Proc. </em>1980;55:758-769.
                        </li>
                        <li>Navarra SV, Guzman RM, Gallacher AE, et al. Efficacy and safety of belimumab in patients with active systemic lupus erythematosus: a randomised, placebo-controlled, phase 3 trial. 
                            <em>Lancet. </em>2011;377:721-731.
                        </li>
                        <li>Furie R, Petri M, Zamani O, et al. A phase III, randomized, placebo-controlled study of belimumab, a monoclonal antibody that inhibits B lymphocyte stimulator, in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2011;63:3918-3930.
                        </li>
                        <li>Stohl W, Schwarting A, Okada M, et al. Efficacy and safety of subcutaneous belimumab in systemic lupus erythematosus: a fifty-two-week randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2017;69:1016-1027.
                        </li>
                        <li>van Vollenhoven RF, Petri MA, Cervera R, et al. Belimumab in the treatment of systemic lupus erythematosus: high disease activity predictors of response. 
                            <em>Ann Rheum Dis. </em>2012;71:1343-1349.
                        </li>
                        <li>Collins CE, Dall'Era M, Kan H, et al. Response to belimumab among patients with systemic lupus erythematosus in clinical practice settings: 24-month results from the OBSErve study in the USA. 
                            <em>Lupus Sci Med. </em>2016;3:e000118.
                        </li>
                        <li>Jordan N, D'Cruz D. Current and emerging treatment options in the management of lupus. 
                            <em>Immunotargets Ther. </em>2016;5:9-20.
                        </li>
                        <li>Mok CC. Current role of rituximab in systemic lupus erythematosus. 
                            <em>Int J Rheum Dis</em>. 2015;18:154-163.
                        </li>
                        <li>Rovin BH, Furie R, Latinis K, et al. Efficacy and safety of rituximab in patients with active proliferative lupus nephritis: the Lupus Nephritis Assessment with Rituximab study. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2012;64:1215-1226.
                        </li>
                        <li>Merrill JT, Neuwelt CM, Wallace DJ, et al. Efficacy and safety of rituximab in moderately-to-severely active systemic lupus erythematosus: the randomized, double-blind, phase ii/iii systemic lupus erythematosus evaluation of rituximab trial. 
                            <em>Arthritis Rheum. </em>2010;62:222-233.
                        </li>
                        <li>Cobo-Ibanez T, Loza-Santamaria E, Pego-Reigosa JM, et al. Efficacy and safety of rituximab in the treatment of non-renal systemic lupus erythematosus: a systematic review. 
                            <em>Semin Arthritis Rheum. </em>2014;44:175-185.
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </subsec_content>
                <qna_form/>
            </subsec_element>
        </sec_element>
        <pg_footnotes/>
    </toc_element>
    <back_label>Back Matter</back_label>
    <layer_grp>
        <layer_img_sm/>
        <layer_img_full/>
        <layer_caption/>
        <layer_label/>
        <layer_alt_txt/>
        <layer_table/>
    </layer_grp>
    <ref_grp>
        <ref_item/>
    </ref_grp>
    <cpyrt_holder>
        <p>Medscape, LLC</p>
    </cpyrt_holder>
    <cpyrt_ovrd/>
    <disclmr_ovrd/>
    <bkmtr_front>
        <p>Developed through a partnership between
            <br/>
            <img alt="Medscape" src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/provider/medscape-logo.png"/>
            <br/>
            <img src="/webmd/professional_assets/medscape/images/provider/lupus-foundation-of-america.jpg"/>
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Disclaimer</strong>
        </p>
        <p>The educational activity presented above may involve simulated case-based scenarios. The patients depicted in these scenarios are fictitious and no association with any actual patient is intended or should be inferred.</p>
        <p>The material presented here does not necessarily reflect the views of Medscape, LLC, or companies that support educational programming on medscape.org. These materials may discuss therapeutic products that have not been approved by the US Food and Drug Administration and off-label uses of approved products. A qualified healthcare professional should be consulted before using any therapeutic product discussed. Readers should verify all information and data before treating patients or employing any therapies described in this educational activity.</p>
    </bkmtr_front>
    <bkmtr_glossary/>
    <bkmtr_ack/>
    <bkmtr_discl/>
    <bkmtr_funding/>
    <bkmtr_reprnt_addr/>
    <bkmtr_abbr_notes/>
    <bkmtr_last/>
    <img_ttl_bkgrd/>
    <img_publ_logo/>
</prof_article>
